<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the negotiation of the ambassadors sent to the Duke of Savoy by the Protestant cantons of Switzerland concerning the Vaudois translated from the original copy printed in Switzerland.</title>
            <title>Histoire l'ambassade envoyée en 1686 par les Suisses au duc de Savoye. English</title>
            <author>Teissier, Antoine, 1632-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13287940</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13287940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98823</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 440:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the negotiation of the ambassadors sent to the Duke of Savoy by the Protestant cantons of Switzerland concerning the Vaudois translated from the original copy printed in Switzerland.</title>
                  <title>Histoire l'ambassade envoyée en 1686 par les Suisses au duc de Savoye. English</title>
                  <author>Teissier, Antoine, 1632-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Histoire l'ambassade envoyée en 1686 par les Suisses au duc de Savoye.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Antoine Teissier. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes translation of the Duke of Savoy's edict concerning the Waldenses.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Waldenses --  Italy --  Piemonte.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:98823:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY of the NEGOTIATION BETWEEN THE DUKE of <hi>SAVOY,</hi> AND THE Proteſtant Cantons OF SWITZERLAND.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98823:2"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Hiſtorical Account of the moſt Remarkable Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions betwixt the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and the <hi>French King;</hi> contained in ſeveral Letters paſt betwixt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Rupture. <hi>Tranſlated from the Original French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A True Relation of the Cruelties and Barbarities of the <hi>French</hi> upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Priſoners of War; being a Journal of their Travels from <hi>Dinan</hi> in <hi>Britanny,</hi> to <hi>Thoulon</hi> in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence,</hi> and back again. With a Deſcription of the Scituation and Fortfiications of all the eminent Towns upon the Road, and their diſtance. Of their Priſons and Hoſpitals, and the number of men that died under their Cruelty; with the Names of many of them, and the places of their Deaths and Burials; with an Account of the great Charity and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the poor Proteſtants of <hi>France;</hi> and other material things that hapned upon the way.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Poems, Satyrs, and Songs againſt Popery and Tyranny, in 4. Parts; moſt of them writ by the late D. of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andr. Marvel,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Aylof,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stephen College.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intrigues of the <hi>French King</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broil <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> diſcover'd in ſeveral Diſpatches paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Him and the late Grand Signior, Grand Vizier, and Count <hi>Teckely;</hi> all of them found in that Count's Papers. With ſome Reflections upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Nonconformiſt;</hi> or, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after a Deprivation incurr'd by the expreſs words of a Statute, fairly ſtated and examined. With ſome ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon Mr. <hi>Cookes</hi> Sermon, <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1690. which was Licens'd by the Archbiſhop's Chaplain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fate of France.</hi> A Diſcourſe where it is ſhew'd, That by the <hi>happy Revolution</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> all the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>Univerſal Monarchy</hi> are diſappointed, and the rational grounds to believe his Downfal near. In Dialogues between F. <hi>Petre,</hi> F. <hi>la Chaiſe,</hi> and two Proteſtant Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſſex's Innocency and Honour vindicated;</hi> or Murther, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornation, Perjury, and Oppreſſion, juſtly charg'd on the Murderers of that Noble Lord, and True Patriot, <hi>Arthur</hi> (late) Earl of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> as proved before the Right Honourable (late) Committee of Lords, <hi>or ready to be depoſed.</hi> By <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence Braddon,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>The Folly of Prieſt-Craft. A Comedy.</p>
            <p>The Royal Flight, or the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland.</hi> A Comedy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98823:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE NEGOTIATION OF THE AMBASSADORS SENT TO THE <hi>Duke of Savoy,</hi> BY THE Proteſtant Cantons OF SWITZERLAND, CONCERNING THE VAUDOIS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the Original Copy printed in</hi> Switzerland.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>LICENS'D, </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>October</hi> 16. 1690.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>J. FRASER.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick Lane.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98823:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98823:3"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY of the NEGOTIATION BETWEEN THE DUKE of <hi>SAVOY,</hi> AND THE Proteſtant Cantons OF SWITZERLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Embaſſy which the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cantons of <hi>Switzerland</hi> ſent to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> in the year 1686. to intercede in favour of the Churches of the Valleys, was both important and difficult; and that it may give place to ſome oppoſite Reflections: I thought ſit to publiſh the Hiſtory of it, that all equitable perſons being informed of what has paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this Negotiation, might be able to make a juſt and reaſonable judgment of it.</p>
            <p>To this effect, I intend to inform you of the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable particulars of this Embaſſy: and as I do not ground my Work but upon good Memorials, and that my Pen ſhall not be miſ-led either by Intereſt, Hatred or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, I hope that if I do not pleaſe my Reader by the eloquence and politeneſs of my Stile, I ſhall be able at
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98823:4"/> leaſt to ſatisfie him by the ſincerity and exactneſs of my Narrative.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain, that amongſt all Proteſtants, the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Cantons have always diſtinguiſhed themſelves by a love they have ſhewed for their Religion, and by an arden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with which they have embraced the Intereſt of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches: As ſoon as the firſt light of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation appeared in <hi>France,</hi> They contributed to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power to advance this Divine Work in that Kingdom; and they diſpatched ſeveral Ambaſſadors to <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, and the Kings his Succeſſors, to deſire them to put a ſtop to the Cruelties of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy, exerciſed againſt thoſe that profeſſed the true Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>They have ſhewed the ſame Zeal in all the Perſecutions the Churches of <hi>Piemont</hi> have been forced to undergo: In thoſe that happened in the year 1655. and 1663. they ſent Ambaſſadors to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to intercede in their favour, and to maintain them in all their Rights they had acquired by the conceſſions of his Anceſtors; and in the year 1686. as ſoon as they were informed of what was contained in the Edict this Prince had publiſhed againſt their Brethren in <hi>Piemont,</hi> they ſhewed they were extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned for it: And whereas this unfortunate Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was attacqued with more Injuſtice than they ever had been before, and that they were threatned with the moſt terrible Evils that could be imagined, they reſolved to leave no ſtone unturned to divert it from them.</p>
            <p>In effect, formerly their Enemies did only propoſe to themſelves to keep them in the narroweſt limits, and to deprive them of the right to inhabit the Plains, which they had always enjoyed; but now there was a deſign laid to deprive them not only of the exerciſe of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion throughout the whole Country, but alſo of Liberty of Conſcience, which made their condition worthy of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>But that we may be able to judge the better of it, it is neceſſary to let you ſee a faithful Tranſlation of this Edict.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98823:4"/>
                  <head>VICTOR AMIDEE, by the Grace of God, Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> and of <hi>Piemont,</hi> and King of <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>POlitick as well as Chriſtian Prudence adviſes us very often to neglect in ſome manner the Ulcers that are not yet in a condition to be healed, and that might be made worſe by a precipitate Cure: This Conduct has been obſerved as well in other Monarchies, as by Our moſt Serene Predeceſſors, who in truth had never any other deſign, than to reſcue their Subjects profeſſing the pretended Reformed Religion, out of the darkneſs of Hereſie, which by an unhappy viciſſitude, and a fatal cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of theſe times, had paſſed from the very Centre of the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> into the very heart of <hi>Piemont.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, by reaſon of the Succours which the Zealots of that Religion did receive from Foreign Countreys, this Holy Work could not be brought to the End We ſo much deſired; inſomuch that not having been able to purge Our Countrey of this Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, We did reduce them to, and ſhut them up in the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> of <hi>St. Martyne,</hi> of <hi>Cernſe,</hi> of <hi>St. Bartholomew,</hi> of <hi>Roccapiara,</hi> and of <hi>Parnſtin;</hi> and by way of Toleration, We did ſuffer them to exerciſe there their falſe Religion, in the limits before preſcribed them, according to the juncture of Times, till it ſhould pleaſe God Almighty to give Us a favourable opportunity of bringing back thoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Souls into the boſom of the Holy and Only Catholick, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick, and Romiſh Religion. Yet time has diſcovered how much it was neceſſary to cut off the numerous Heads of this <hi>Hydra,</hi> ſince the ſaid Hereticks, inſtead of anſwering this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with a deep ſubmiſſion, and with a ſincere acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this kind Toleration, have very often made bold to be diſobedient, to a ſcandal, and to riſe againſt their own So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe at preſent the principal Cauſe of this ſaid To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration is now removed by the Zeal and Piety of the Glorious Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> who has brought back to the true Faith his neighbouring Hereticks; We think the particular Graces We have received from His Divine Majeſty, and which We
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98823:5"/> enjoy ſtill, would accuſe Us of the greateſt ingratitude, if by our negligence We ſhould let ſlip the opportunity of executing this Work, according to the intention of Our Glorious Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. It is for this, and ſeveral urgent Reaſons, that by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this preſent Edict, with Our full Knowledge, and by Our abſolute Power, as alſo by the Advice of Our Council, We have Declared and Ordered, and do Declare and Order by theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, to Our Subjects of the pretended Reformed Religion, to deſiſt for the future from all the Exerciſe of the ſaid Religion. And We do prohibit them further, after the publiſhing this Edict, to hold no Aſſemblies or Conventicles in any place or particular Houſe to exerciſe the ſaid Religion, under what title, pretext, or occaſion whatſoever, under pain of their Lives, and Confiſcation of their Goods. And We Ordain alſo, That the paſt pretended Toleration be of no effect, under what colour or pretence whatſoever. Our Will is alſo, That all the Churches, Granges and Houſes, in which at preſent the ſaid Religion is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, ſhall be raſed to the ground; as alſo all other places in which for the future ſuch Aſſemblies ſhall be held, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of what the precedent Articles contains; and this is to be executed, tho the Owners of ſuch places are ignorant thereof. And We Command accordingly all Eccleſiaſticks, Miniſters and Schoolmaſters of the ſaid pretended Reformed Religion, who in one fortnight after the publiſhing this preſent Edict, do not effectually embrace the Catholick Religion, ſhall retreat out of our Territories after the ſaid term be paſt, under pain of Death, and Confiſcation of their Goods; with expreſs Command, and under the ſame Puniſhment, not to make, within the ſaid time, or before their departure, any Sermon, Exhortation, or any other Act if the ſaid Religion. And furthermore, We forbid, under the ſaid Puniſhment, and the forfeiture of Our ſavour, all thoſe that make Profeſſion of the pretended Reformed Religion, to keep for the future any publick or private School; it being Our intention, That from this very time their Children ſhall be inſtructed by Catholick Schoolmaſters. And concerning the Miniſters who within the ſaid time ſhall embrace the Catholick Religion, Our Will and Pleaſure is, That during their Lives, and after they are dead, their Widows, as long as they ſhall live unmarried, ſhall enjoy the ſaid Exemptions and Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which they enjoyed heretofore, during the exerciſe of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98823:5"/> Charge. And Our Will is over and above, That to the ſaid Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks who ſhall be made Converts in the ſaid manner, there ſhall be paid during their life a Penſion one third part lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the Sallary was which they enjoyed in quality of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters of the ſaid Religion; and that after their death their Widows enjoy one half of the ſaid Penſion as long as they ſhall continue unmarried. And concerning the Children that ſhall be born by Father and Mother of the ſaid pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, Our intention is, That after the publiſhing this preſent Edict, they ſhall be baptized by the Prieſts of the Pariſh that are already, or that ſhall be eſtabliſhed for the future in the ſaid Valleys: to this purpoſe, We Command their Fathers and Mothers to ſend or bring them to the Churches, under pain of being ſent five years to the Galleys for their Fathers, and whipping for their Mothers; and moreover, the ſaid Children ſhall be brought up in the ſaid Catholick, Apoſtolick, and <hi>Roman</hi> Religion. And We Command expreſly all Judges, Bailiffs, Gaclers, and other Officers, to ſee theſe Preſents duly executed. And We do confirm alſo the Edict We have publiſhed the 4th of <hi>November</hi> paſt, concerning the Subjects of His Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſty that make profeſſion of the pretended Reformed Religion, and that are to be found in Our Territories, and that have left their Merchandiſes, Money, or other Effects behind them; and concerning the other Foreigners of the ſaid Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who, to the prejudice of ſome of Our Prediceſſors Edicts, have eſtabliſhed themſelves in the Valleys, without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in writing, comprehending therein their Off-ſpring that are born there: We Command, That in caſe, within one fortnight after the publiſhing this preſent Edict, they do not declare to be willing to embrace the Catholick, Apoſtolick, and <hi>Roman</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they ſhall be obliged, if the ſaid term be paſt, to repeat cut of Our Territories, under pain of Death, and Confiſcation of their Goods. And tho lawfully, by virtue of the ſaid Edicts, the Goods which the ſaid Foreigners have acquired in Our Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories ought to be confiſcated for Our Royal Treaſury; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs We are willing in this caſe to ſhew Our accuſtomed Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, and to give them leave to ſell their ſaid Goods (if they pleaſe) within the ſaid term, and to diſpoſe of the ſame as they think convenient: Yet upon theſe Conditions, That the ſelling the unmovable Goods ſhall only be made in favour of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98823:6"/> but in caſe they ſhall find no Buyer, they ſhall be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as ſold, and united to Our Dominions under a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble price. Finally, We Command all the Magiſtrates eſtabliſhed by Us, Miniſters of State, Officers, Judges, and all others whom it concerns, to ſee this preſent Edict inviolably obſerved; and ſo to order the ſame, that the Council of <hi>Piemont</hi> may enroll it, and give their full approbation of what is contained therein. Moreover, Our Will is, That the Publiſhing made hereof in the accuſtomed places, and in the ordinary man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſhall have the ſame virtue as if it had been made known to every particular perſon; and that there be the ſame obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance paid to the Copy hereof, Printed by <hi>Sinibal</hi> Our Printer, as to this My Original it ſelf; FOR THIS IS OUR WILL. <hi>Given at</hi> Turin, January <hi>31. 1686.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By His Royal Highneſs's Command, VICTOR AMIDEO. <hi>Deſt. Thomas.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Proteſtant Cantons having been inform'd of this Edict, did alſo underſtand ſome time after, that the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Valleys had endeavoured, tho without ſucceſs, to find ſome remedy againſt it; for they did preſent two Petitions to their Prince, that were not anſwered: In the firſt, they deſired the Edict ſhould be revok'd; and in the ſecond, they asked leave to retreat out of his Territories within ſuch a time as would be neceſſary to find out an Eſtabliſhment ſomewhere elſe.</p>
            <p>The Cantons ſeeing that the ordinary means which were made uſe of to hinder the execution of this Edict, had no effect, did think that they ought to employ ſome extraordinary ones. Accordingly they writ a Letter imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> deſiring him that he might be pleaſed to maintain his Subjects of the Valleys in the Privileges which were granted them by his Predeceſſors: and finding that this Prince made no great haſte to ſend them an Anſwer, but that on the contrary he was in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to execute his Edict by force, they reſolved in a Diet at <hi>Baden,</hi> in the month of <hi>February,</hi> 1686. to diſpatch him two Ambaſſadors, in order to endeavour to obtain by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98823:6"/> their Repreſentations, what they could not obtain by their Letters.</p>
            <p>The perſons that were pitch'd upon, were <hi>Caſpar de Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratt,</hi> and <hi>Bernard de Muratt,</hi> Councellors of State, the firſt of <hi>Zurich,</hi> and the other of <hi>Bern,</hi> that had both all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary qualities to acquit themſelves worthily in this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, in regard of their Vertue and Piety, as well as their Prudence and Capacity.</p>
            <p>Theſe Ambaſſadors were charged to employ their utmoſt endeavours to oblige the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to revoke the Edict he had publiſhed againſt the Churches of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys; and becauſe there was ſome reaſon of fear that His Royal Highneſs might perſiſt in his deſign to execute it in all its Points, the Evangelical Cantons, after having well conſidered the condition of thoſe that compoſed thoſe Churches, as alſo the Alliance and Forces of that Prince that was reſolved entirely to extirpate them, in caſe they refuſed to ſubmit to his Will, thought that in caſe their Ambaſſadors could by no means obtain the revoking of that Edict, it would be expedient that they ſhould employ themſelves to procure thoſe miſerable wretches the liberty to retreat into ſome other Country, to ſell their Goods, and to carry along with them what they ſhould be able to ſave out of their ſhattered Fortunes.</p>
            <p>The Lords that were of this Aſſembly were too wiſe and too judicious to think upon other means than theſe. They ſaw at one hand, the little number of thoſe that were able to carry Arms in the Valleys; for they were at the moſt but 2500 Men, for the moſt part ill Arm'd, that had no Head, that were ill provided with Ammunition and Proviſions, that had no hopes of Succours from any place, and that thoſe that were their Commanders in the years 1655, and 1664. were not alive.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, when they did conſider the Forces of that Prince, who was reſolved to aboliſh their Religion, they found that they far exceeded thoſe of His Subjects, that were of a contrary Perſuaſion; for the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> had enjoy'd a very long Peace, he had a great number of good Troops, brave Captains, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd Generals. He had nothing to fear either from his Neighbours, or any other Prince of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98823:7"/>
            <p>And ſo much the more, becauſe the Troops of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> were joyn'd by the Forces of the <hi>French</hi> King, ſo dreadful at that time, that his very Name made moſt Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> tremble, inſtead that formerly the Subjects of this Monarch fought jointly with thoſe of the Vallies, to ſecure them from the Oppreſſion of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign; and that notwithſtanding the Succours they had from other hands, they were driven out of their Vallies, and were not able to defend themſelves againſt the only Forces of their Prince.</p>
            <p>Moreover they conſidered, that if by an unlook'd-for Succeſs, the Inhabitants of the Vallies ſhould gain ſome Advantage over their Enemies; that at laſt, they would be forced to give way to the great Number of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, whoſe Loſſes might be eaſily redreſſed by ſome freſh Troops; but that on the contrary, the <hi>Vaudois</hi> would have no means to make Recruits inſtead of thoſe that would be loſt in their ſeveral Fights, to which they would be expoſed.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that having to deal with the <hi>French</hi> King, who is the proudeſt Prince in the World, and who at that time was not troubled with any Enemy, he would rather have armed againſt them all the Inhabitants of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, than to have run the hazard of deſiſting from an Enterprize, which he lookt upon as one of the moſt Glorious he ever undertook, and which he thought ſhould acquire him an eminent place amongſt the greateſt Saints in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice.</p>
            <p>And whereas they had before their Eyes thoſe <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> that were ſhelter'd in their Territories, they did compare their Condition with that of their Brethren in <hi>Piemont,</hi> and they found that conſidering the great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity theſe laſt were reduced to, if they could get Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to leave their Country, they would be much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier than the other that were forced not only to leave their Houſes, Goods, and Native Country, but that could not buy their Exile, but with the hazard of their Lives and Liberties.</p>
            <p>In fine, they thought they could do nothing more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious for the <hi>Piemonteſe,</hi> than to obtain what they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98823:7"/> had themſelves deſired in the Age paſt, as well as in this, when they were troubled about the Exerciſe of their Religion; for in thoſe times they humbly Petition'd their Prince to grant them leave to Retreat into ſome other Countries.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors having received their Inſtructions, went for <hi>Piemont;</hi> and preſently after their arrival at <hi>Turin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing introduced to His Royal Highneſs's Audience, they did repreſent to him, That whereas the Interceſſion of the Proteſtant Cantons, their Lords, in favour of His Royal Highneſs's Subjects of the Valleys, making Profeſſion of the Reformed Religion, had always been agreeable to him, and produced ſuch an Effect, as they could have wiſh'd for; their Sovereign Lords having with great Grief un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that His Royal Highneſs had form'd a Deſign to deprive his ſaid Subjects of their Liberty of Conſcience, and of the Exerciſe of their Religion, which they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd during ſeveral Ages, had been moved by a Chriſtian Charity, by a ſtrict Union which they are join'd with to thoſe of their Communion, and by a Confidence of His Royal Highneſs's Clemency and Juſtice, to intercede in their Letters of Recommendation in favour of their Brethren in the Valleys.</p>
            <p>But having received no Anſwer, they had charged them with this Embaſſy, in order to demonſtrate the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration they have for His Royal Highneſs, and at the ſame time to ſhew how ſenſibly they were touch'd by the laſt Edict, which he had publiſhed againſt His poor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Vallies; and had given them order to aſſure him of their ſtrict Adherency to his Intereſt, and to deſire him afterwards inſtantly, that he would be pleaſed to maintain the Inhabitants of the Valleys in a perpetual and peaceful Enjoyment of the Exerciſe of their Religion, and in that Liberty of Conſcience which was granted them by his Predeceſſors, upon the Interceding and Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of ſeveral Proteſtant Princes and States, and particularly of their Sovereign Lords; and that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which gave them ſome hopes to obtain what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, was, that His Subjects had done nothing that could render them unworthy of the Favour and Affection of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98823:8"/> their Prince, or that ſhould deprive them of a Right they had acquired by ſuch Grants, as ought to be inviolable, becauſe they were no ſimple Tolerations, but Authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Treaties made with the Inhabitants of the Valleys, and that conſequently ought to be perpetual and irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, as it is ſeen in the 20th Article of the Patent of the year 1655. and in the 19th Article of that of the year 1664. that ſay, That they ſhall be perpetually and irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably obſerved, and that in effect they have been inroll'd by the Senate of <hi>Chambery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in Order to be executed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Form and Contents.</p>
            <p>That their Lords were firmly perſwaded, that his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs would not ſuffer, that in his ſo happy and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reign, theſe Patents, followed by ſeveral Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a world of ſolemn Promiſes, ſhould be Cancell'd; and that the Fruits of their Mediation, of their Care, and of their Pains, ſhould be reduced to nothing.</p>
            <p>That he would not have it ſhould be thought, that he had not for the Proteſtant Cantons the ſame Regard, and the ſame Conſiderations which his Anceſtors had; that that perfect Friendſhip and ſincere Correſpondency which has always been entertained between his Royal Highneſs, and their Lords, as between good Friends and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſhould in the leaſt be changed; that his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhould be expoſed to a world of Troubles and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; that the Conſciences of his Subjects, that ought not to be anſwerable but to God, ſhould be forced by fear of Death and Torments; and in a word, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of his Valleys ſhould be oppreſs'd with Miſery, and brought to deſpair.</p>
            <p>That therefore they pray'd his Royal Highneſs with all poſſible Ardency, well to receive the Interceſſion of their Sovereigns in Favour of his Subjects, as their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by a Communion of the ſame Religion, and to be touched by the Sighs and Tears of ſo many Innocent Souls, who humbly did entreat him to ſuſpend the Execution of his Edict, and not to turn his Arms againſt his own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who paying that Religious Homage to God, which is due to him, deſired to Seal up by the loſs of all their Blood, that Allegiance which they had ſworn to his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98823:8"/>
            <p>That in caſe their Mediation ſhould produce the effect their Sovereign Lords ſo much wiſht for, it would be the moſt convincing Mark his Royal Highneſs could give them, that he made no leſs Reflection of their Entremiſe, than his Predeceſſors of Glorious Memory had done; and that on their ſide they would endeavour to find means to ſhew him their acknowledgment, and to render him their reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal Services on all occaſions.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Miniſters of State of his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Conferences the Ambaſſadors have had with them, did mention ſome reaſons, why his Royal Highneſs had publiſhed that Edict, which they deſired ſhould be revoked: The Ambaſſadors thought it neceſſary to Anſwer them, and to ſupport their Demand by the Reaſons ſet down in this following Memorial.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>WHereas the Right Honourable the Miniſters of State of his Royal Highneſs, have given us to underſtand upon a private Information of our Reaſons, that his preſent Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and into which he did not enter but by the neceſſity of the preſent Juncture of the Times, was a great Obſtacle to the Succeſs of our Negotiation; we find our ſelves obliged to repreſent to your Royal Highneſs, That the Churches of the Valleys in <hi>Piemont,</hi> did not ſeparate themſelves from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of their Prince, becauſe they live in that they received from their Predeceſſors above Eight Ages ago, and which they did profeſs before they were under the Dominion of Your Royal Highneſs's Anceſtors, who having found them in the Poſſeſſion of their Religion, have maintained them therein by ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and principally by thoſe of the year <hi>1561, 1602,</hi> and <hi>1603.</hi> which having been enrolled by the Parliament of <hi>Chambery,</hi> in the year <hi>1620.</hi> for the Sum of <hi>6000 French Ducate,</hi> which theſe Churches paid them, as the very act of enrolling mentions, their Right paſſed into a Form of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, and into a perpetual and irrevocable Law, which has been obſerved during the Life of his Royal Highneſs <hi>Victor Amadee,</hi> and during the Regency of Madam <hi>Royale,</hi> who confirmed them by her Declaration in the year <hi>1638.</hi> Theſe Churches have in following times obtained ſeveral other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Declarations of his Royal Highneſs, <hi>Charles Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98823:9"/> of Glorious Memory, Your Royal Highneſs's Father, in particular, in the year <hi>1649,</hi> and <hi>1653.</hi> But whereas to the prejudice of a Right ſo well eſtabliſhed by a Poſſeſſion out of Mens Memory, and by ſo many Declarations, the <hi>Sieur Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaldo</hi> did nevertheleſs in the Month of <hi>February, 1655.</hi> publiſh a Declaration, that did produce ſome terrible and fatal Conſequences to theſe poor Churches; all Proteſtant Kings, Princes, and States of <hi>Europe,</hi> and particularly our Sovereign Lords did concern themſelves in their Misfortune, and having interceded in their Favour, by his Royal Highneſs <hi>Charles-Emanuel,</hi> they obtained a Confirmation of their Priviledges, and of their Conceſſions, by two ſolemn perpetual and inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Patents, of the year <hi>1655,</hi> and <hi>1664.</hi> enrolled in a good Form, and confirmed by the Letters he did write to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lords, the 28th of <hi>February, 1664.</hi> by which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them to ſee theſe Patents faithfully executed. To which the Royal Madam, your Royal Highneſſes Mother, did engage her ſelf alſo, by her Letters dated <hi>January</hi> the 28th, <hi>1679.</hi> Therefore, becauſe your Royal Highneſs's Anceſtors had ſeveral times ſolemnly engaged their Royal Word, principally in thoſe Patents that were granted in the preſence of the Ambaſſadors our Sovereigns had ſent to that purpoſe, it would not be juſt to break ſo many formal and authentical Engagements, not only becauſe theſe Priviledges and Patents, being granted in the ſight of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and by the Mediation and Interceſſion of ſeveral Kings, Princes, and States, they are Pledges and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Monuments of the publick Faith; but alſo, becauſe the Words and Promiſes of Sovereigns ought to be Sacred and Inviolable. If Engagements of this Nature might be annulled under pretence of a neceſſity, to which the Juncture of Affairs might reduce a Prince, or of ſome Conveniency and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Eſtate, then there would be nothing aſſured in the World, and nothing would be ſeen there, but War and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. This Maxim being once eſtabliſhed amongſt Sovereigns, the Proteſtant Princes might as lawfully deſtroy the Catholicks that are under their Dominions, as the Catholicks would have a right to extirpate their Proteſtant Subjects. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is evident, that whether we examine the thing, as relating to the Glory and Reputation of the Prince; or if we conſider it according to the Principles of true and juſt Politicks,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98823:9"/> that has no other end than the Security of Sovereign Nations and States, we'll find that the words of Princes ought always to be Inviolable. It is for this Reaſon that we are perſwaded, that no neceſſity of the preſent Junctures, nor any Intereſt will oblige ſo Juſt, ſo Gracious, and ſo wiſe a Prince, as your Royal Highneſs, to follow a new Engagement, that does not only deſtroy all your Predeceſſors have done in the Eyes of the whole Univerſe, but that expoſes alſo your own State and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the Flames, Butchery, Calamities, Devaſtation, and to the moſt cruel and inhumane Rage and Tyranny.</p>
                  <p>It is agreed, that it is natural for a pious Prince to wiſh there was but one Religion in his Countrey; and that being perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that his own is the true one, it did belong to his Duty and Charity to do all he can to perſuade his Subjects to it. But it ought to be allowed alſo, that Religion enters into our hearts by means of perſuaſion, and not by force; and that to convince one of the Divide Truth, there ought to be employed nothing but Inſtruction, Sweetneſs, and Exhortation, according to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p>That Kings and Princes, tho they are Maſters of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet they have no Empire over their Conſciences, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend alone from God; inſomuch that we have reaſon to hope, that your Royal Highneſs, far from forcing your Subjects to do things againſt their Conſciences, you will be pleaſed, on the contrary, to reſtore them their Peace, which we implore for them, to confirm their Privileges, and to let them enjoy the liberty to <hi>give God that which is due to Him,</hi> whilſt at the ſame time they pay your Royal Highneſs that Reſpect and Homage which they owe You, as your faithful Subjects.</p>
                  <p>My Lords the Miniſters of State, have told us alſo, That the Inhabitants of the Valleys had rendred themſelves unworthy of their Prince's favour: But beſides that all the world agrees, that before the publiſhing of the firſt Edict, they had given your Royal Highneſs no reaſon of Complaints; and that, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, it is not their ill Conduct has drawn upon them ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous an Order; and that if there were ſome amongſt them that had committed a fault, (which we are yet ignorant of) we ought not to be ſurprized, if ſome miſerable wretches, that are brought to deſpair, ſhould do ſome imprudent actions. Beſides all this, we ſay, Your Royal Highneſs is too gracious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98823:10"/> 
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98823:10"/> 
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98823:11"/> and too good not to pardon faults of this nature; and too juſt and equitable to puniſh the Publick for an Exceſs that may have been committed by ſome particular perſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In fine,</hi> They would make us believe, That thoſe Patents his Royal Highneſs <hi>Charles-Emanuel</hi> granted in the year <hi>1655,</hi> and <hi>1664.</hi> did not concern Religion, but give them leave only to inhabit ſome certain places in the Valleys; and that, conſequently, our Sovereign Lords, and the other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that were Mediators in this Affair, had no Interest in it.</p>
                  <p>But we beg your Royal Highneſs to conſider, <hi>firſt,</hi> That <hi>Religion</hi> was then ſo much the Subject of the Queſtion, that properly no other things did belong to it; for beſides that the Order of the Sieur <hi>Gaſtaldo,</hi> that produced ſo many diſmal Conſequences, did deſtroy theſe Conceſſions that were granted to the Inhabitants of the Valleys about Religion, it was pretended at that time to force them to do things againſt their Conſcience, becauſe they were threatned with Death, and Confiſcation of their Goods, that would not embrace the <hi>Catholick Religion</hi> within twenty days after they were ordered to do it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> All the Mediation and Interceſſion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes and States, were only grounded on things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> They have only acted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Principle, and the Ambaſſadors were for no other reaſon received and heard, but by reaſon of the Intereſt they took in a buſineſs concerning Religion: And it is for this reaſon, that your Royal Highneſs's Predeceſſors have given ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral aſſurances, by Letters to their Excellencies the Evangelical Cantons, that the Patents granted upon their requeſt ſhould be punctually and faithfully executed.</p>
                  <p>And, becauſe to the prejudice of all that has been granted them, your Royal Highneſs has publiſhed an Edict that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids them the Exerciſe of their Religion in all the Valleys, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pain of Death; that commands the demoliſhing all the Churches, that does baniſh the Miniſters and Schoolmaſters, that commands that the Children ſhall be baptized, and brought up in the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> and that deprives by theſe means thoſe People of their Liberty of Conſcience: Our Sovereign Lords, that are united to the Churches of the Valleys by the ſame Faith, are obliged to continue to intercede for them:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98823:11"/> And it is this we do now in their name, in hopes that your Royal Highneſs will be couo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed by ſome conſideration of our Sovereign Lords, and by ſome Compaſſion for your Subjects.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors having delivered their Memorial to the Marqueſs <hi>de St. Thomas,</hi> one of his Royal Highneſs's Miniſters of State that had the direction of the Foreign Affairs, they receiv'd few days after an Anſwer to this purpoſe: That his Royal Highneſs was ſorry that he was not in a capacity to grant what they deſired in their own and in their Maſter's Name; That he had far ſtronger reaſons to maintain this Edict, than they had given him to revoke it; and that he could not do as much as to miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate it. That the great Wheels moved and carried along with them the little ones. That the Letter the Proteſtant Cantons had writ to him, had not been delivered to him but after the Edict was publiſhed. That having to his Neighbour a Prince equally Powerful, and jealous of his Authority, he was obliged to carry himſelf with a great deal of circumſpection, and to act according to the jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the times, in the ſame manner as in <hi>Switzerland</hi> they were ſometimes forced, by the turning of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to take ſome reſolutions contrary to the good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they might have otherways. That the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> had given good and profitable Advice to the two Deputies of the Valleys that were ſent to him; and that, inſtead of giving him ſome marks of their ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and deference they were bound to, they had exercis'd all manner of Hoſtilities againſt his other Subjects, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a thouſand inſolent things, and held ſome ſecret Conventicles. That they were provided with Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Proviſions. That they had rendred themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Paſſages. That they had rerench'd themſelves; and that they had done all this within the time of fifteen or twenty days, which had been allowed them to take their laſt Reſolutions. That the Prince was too far engaged. That the Troops which he had raiſed with great Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, were now on foot. That the Edict could not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, without wounding his Royal Highneſs's Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That he was forced to ſee it executed, for very
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98823:12"/> ſtrong Reaſons, on which he would let the Ambaſſadors make their reflections. That the Grants of 1655, and 1664. were a meer Toleration; and that the Valleys had no poſitive Right to exerciſe their Religion. That So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns do no injuſtice in not being willing to ſuffer more than one Religion in their Countrey; and that the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Cantons themſelves juſtified his Royal Highneſs's Conduct, by not enduring <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks amongſt them. Moreover, That the Conceſſions granted to thoſe of the Valleys, had been juridically examin'd; and that it was agreed, that the Conceſſions and Favours a Prince grants to his Subjects, may be revoked according to his pleaſure. That his Royal Highneſs did forbid the Inhabitants of the Valleys nothing but the Exerciſe of their Religion, but that he did no ways intend to force their Conſciences.</p>
            <p>But the Ambaſſadors by their Reply told the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> That how ſtrong ſoever his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's Reaſons were to conſent to his Edict of <hi>January</hi> laſt, they could not prevail over thoſe that did neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to obſerve the promiſes given before this Edict. That ſome conſiderations of State ought not to diſpence a Prince from performing his Word, principally if he be entred into this Engagement by the Mediation of another Sovereign; and that whereas the Patents and Conceſſions granted to the Inhabitants of the Valleys had been acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Interceſſion of ſeveral Kings, Princes, and States, and, in particular, of their Excellencies the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cantons, and confirmed by his Royal Highneſs, he could allege nothing that might diſcharge him from the Obligation of ſeeing them punctually obſerved; and the rather, becauſe theſe Patents have been enrolled by the Parliament of <hi>Savoy;</hi> and that the only enrolling of the year 1620. had coſt the Churches of the Valleys 6000 Crowns.</p>
            <p>That, in caſe ſome Changes happening in a State, or ſeveral Reflections that could be made according to the Rules of Politicks, were proper exceptions to elude the Obſervation of Treaties, there would be no aſſurance in a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98823:12"/> Sovereign's Promiſe, Faith and Honeſty would be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther baniſhed ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Commerce. And ſince no body could be aſſured of the execution of thoſe things which they had agreed upon, there would be left no means to terminate Wars, and to conclude Alliances.</p>
            <p>That therefore the Conceſſions granted by the Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of his Royal Highneſs to the Inhabitants of the Valleys, did acquire them an unconteſtable Right, which they could not loſe but by an enormous Crime, and by a Rebellion againſt their lawful Sovereign; and that, far from being guilty of any want of their Duty, they could produce a Letter of his Royal Highneſs's, of the 2d of <hi>September</hi> 1684. which is an authentical and glorious proof of their Fidelity, and an inviolable adherency which they had always ſhewed to their Prince's Intereſt.</p>
            <p>That if in caſe, after the publication of the laſt Edict, ſome particular perſons amongſt them had taken up Arms, they had not done it to make uſe of them againſt their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, but only to defend themſelves againſt thoſe that abuſing his Authority, had undertaken to attacque and to inſult them; and that in caſe there had been ſome diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der committed, thoſe that were the Authors ought to be puniſhed; but that it ought not to be imputed to the whole Body of the Churches of the Valleys, that were in no manner guilty of it.</p>
            <p>That it could not be ſaid, that the Inhabitants of the Valleys had acquired no Right by the Grants of his Royal Highneſs's Predeceſſors; and that they were not only ſome Favours and ſimple Tolerations; it being notorious, that they are Treaties made between the Prince and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and that theſe Treaties are perpetual and irrevoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ought to be inviolably obſerved.</p>
            <p>That the Prince was equally obliged to execute the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes he had made to his Subjects, as thoſe that regarded ſuch perſons that are in no manner under his Submiſſion. That ſuch Obligations were grounded upon publick Faith and Honeſty, which ought to rule in all Treaties of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereigns, without diſtinctions of thoſe with which they did engage themſelves; That if it was allowable to fail in what they had ſolemnly promiſed to their people, it would be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98823:13"/> impoſſible to terminate Affairs that ſhould ariſe between them, nor to appeaſe theſe troubles that happen in their State; and that two Parties ſhould make War on one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would never end their quarrels, but by the total Ruin of one of them.</p>
            <p>They added to this, That Sovereigns had reaſon to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their utmoſt endeavours to unite their Subjects in the ſame Religion; but that to compaſs it, they ought not to violate Treaties which had been formerly made with them. That all that was allow'd them in ſuch a caſe, was, to employ Inſtruction and Exhortation, and all the winning ways of ſweetneſs, that are effectual to make truth enter into the Souls of their People, to chear their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and to move them to embrace with good will the true Religion: But that which deſerved a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration in this Encounter, is, That the Inhabitants of the Valleys did not hold by the Conceſſions of their Princes the liberty to exerciſe in publick their Religion, becauſe it was eſtabliſhed in this Country above eight Ages ago, and that they enjoy'd this Right long time before they were Subjects to his Royal Highneſs's Anceſtors; inſomuch that having never been of the Religion of their Prince, it could not be ſaid that they had abandon'd it, nor oblige them to return to it.</p>
            <p>Beſides that, his Royal Highneſs's Predeceſſors, who did grant leave to the Inhabitants of the Valleys to continue the exerciſe of their Religion, were very ſenſible that Unity of Religion was not neceſſary to the Advantage and Security of the State, for elſe they would have been very far from granting them ſo ſolemn Parents, or from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them from time to time, as they have done.</p>
            <p>And indeed they had ſo much the leſs to fear from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Religion which is found in <hi>Piemont,</hi> that thoſe that were not of his Communion, were ſhut up in a little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Country; that they were Men without Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or Power, and that had no deſign to extend their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to the other parts of his Countries.</p>
            <p>That, on the other hand, he had reaſon to fear, that his Example ſhould be followed by the Proteſtant Princes; and that, in his imitation, they did not uſe their Catholick
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98823:13"/> Subjects in the ſame manner that he would uſe thoſe of their Religion; and that, conſequently, the Intereſt of thoſe of his own Party ſhould hinder him from making uſe of force to oblige the Inhabitants of the Valleys to renounce their Faith.</p>
            <p>That though it ſeemed his Royal Highneſs would not force them to embrace the Romiſh Religion, in that he was ſatisfied to deprive them of the publick Exerciſe of their Religion, leaving them as to the reſt in a full Liberty of Conſcience; yet it was viſible, that they were not only obliged, under rigorous Penalties, to baptize their Children in the Catholick Churches, and to bring them up in the Romiſh Religion; which was as inſupportable to them, as if they were forced themſelves to make profeſſion of it: But that, moreover, being hindred to pray to God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Faith, their Conſciences ſuffered as great tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and lay almoſt under as cruel conſtraints, as if they were obliged by force to practice a Worſhip which is condemned by that Religion in which they have been educated.</p>
            <p>Beſides, That forbidding the People the exerciſe of their Religion, is to throw them into a diſſolution, and Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm it ſelf; and conſequently, to cauſe them a greater Evil than if they were forced to enter into the Romiſh Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons were ſo ſtrong, that the Ambaſſadors ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped they would have ſome effect in his Royal Highneſs's mind; and that the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make them known to him, and employ his Credit which he had with him, to obtain the revoking of an Edict which, without doubt, he had thought to be juſt, and which he would not have publiſhed, if he had been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that it was contrary to what a juſt and equitable Sovereign owes to his faithful Subjects.</p>
            <p>But they did not content themſelves to repreſent the good Right of the <hi>Piemonteſe</hi> Churches, and to ſupport them by ſolid Reaſons, for they employ'd ſeveral days in ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all the Miniſters of his Royal Highneſs, and all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they judged capable to contribute to the Succeſs of their Embaſſy: But above all, they ſtuck cloſe to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98823:14"/> of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> as one from whom depended all the Good and all the Evil they could expect in this Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter; and if we ought to judge of things by their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, the pains they took to diſpoſe him to be favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them, were not altogether unſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>For he did proteſt upon Oath, that they had expoſed to his Royal Highneſs the Contents of the Reply, which he had been charged to preſent to him; that he had done all he could to make him ſenſible of the Reaſons they made uſe of to obtain the revoking the Edict; but that the Juncture of Affairs was the cauſe that he could not perſwade his Royal Highneſs to grant them their Requeſts. <hi>Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> added he, <hi>whereas the Prince's Troups are not yet upon March, the Inhabitants of the Vallies may make a ſhew as if they were willing to execute the Edict, becauſe that ſuch a Conduct is not contrary to the Maxims of your Religion, that are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in oppoſite to the Doctrine of the Catholick-Church, and by theſe means they will diſarm the Prince, and they may find after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſome means to prevent the Evils they are threatned with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Doctrine (anſwered the Ambaſſadors) does in no ways approve the diſſembling of our Faith, and oblige us to profeſs before man the Truth whereof our hearts are perſwaded. But this is not our buſineſs at preſent; the Queſtion is, to know whether His Royal Highneſs could lawfully revoke the Conceſſions granted to the Churches of the Vallies. Now, whereas they are Ingagements in which he is entred by the mediation of ſeveral Sovereigns, and amongſt others by that of the <hi>Laudable Cantons</hi> our Sovereign Lords, it is evident that nothing is capable to break them.</p>
            <p>Yet to neglect nothing of what could contribute to the ſucceſs of their Negotiation, the Ambaſſador made ſome new Efforts both by the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the other Miniſters of His Royal Highneſs; but they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all, (as they had concerted their Anſwer) That the Edict was irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable by reaſon of the preſent Junctures, and ſome meaſures which his Royal Highneſs had taken.</p>
            <p>And becauſe beſides the Reaſons drawn from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Conceſſions granted to the Inhabitants of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98823:14"/> Vallies, and the intereſt the Cantons had to ſee them ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, they repreſented the inconvenience that might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the execution of the Edict, and amongſt others, thoſe his Royal Highneſs had reaſon to fear from the entring of Forreign Troops into his Territories, of the loſs of conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of his Subjects, that had rendred ſeveral important ſervices to their Prince, and that were in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to ſpill all their Blood, to ſignalize their love which they bore him; of the diminiſhing of his Revenues, which would neceſſarily follow the deſtruction of thoſe Wretches; to which they added the blame his Royal Highneſs would draw upon him by turning his Arms againſt his own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; the damage which a Civil War would cauſe to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subjects that were neighbours to the Vallies; with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Conſidererations of this nature. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Prince had no regard for them, and gave the Ambaſſadors to underſtand, That the Council of State ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving examin'd them, did judge they were not ſtrong enough to hinder the Prince from publiſhing his Edict againſt his Subjects of the Vallies, and that ſuppoſing the Edict ſhould really cauſe ſome inconvenience to his Royal Highneſs, he would nevertheleſs not deſiſt from it, for fear a charge of this nature ſhould be a prejudice to his Authority; and that endeavouring to preſerve ſome of his Subjects, he might run the hazard to loſe them all. And though the Miniſters ſeemed to be firm in their Sentiments, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they were not convinced at the Juſtice of the Demands the Ambaſſadors made, it was well known that they did maintain the Edict againſt their own Opinion, and one of them did confeſs frankly, that his Royal Highneſs's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil had not enough examined the Conceſſions of the year 1655. and 1664, and that in caſe they had made ſome neceſſary Reflections on them, they would never have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed the Prince to revoke them; but he did aſſure them, that the Evil was now without remedy, and that the Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations of the Ambaſſador to oblige the Prince to change his Will, would be in vain; and one of the Miniſters frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſed, that the Prince was Maſter of this Affair, and that they executed at <hi>Turin</hi> thoſe Orders that were given at <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98823:15"/>
            <p>This ſincere Confeſſion made the Ambaſſadors judge that all their Inſtances and Solicitations would produce no Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; therefore ſeeing it would be impoſſible for them to obtain the revokation of the Edict, they thought fit accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the chief head of their Inſtructions, to demand that which related to the Second Article of the Orders they had received from their Sovereigns, <hi>viz.</hi> To procure the Inhabitants of the Vallies the means to retreat ſome where elſe, and to diſpoſe of their goods as they ſhould think fit.</p>
            <p>But becauſe their inſtruction was, to make about this Point no Propoſals to the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> but with the conſent of the Inhabitants of the Vallies, they told the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> that whereas for ſeveral reaſons they had entertained no correſpondency with them, they were willing to make a journey into the Vallies, to inform themſelves exactly of the diſpoſition of this People, and to get means by the acquaintance of their intentions, to make ſome overtures of a new Negotiation. But they gave him to underſtand at the ſame time, they would by no means undertake this Voyage, but with his Royal Highneſs's full conſent.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> having acquainted his Royal Highneſs with the deſign of the Ambaſſadors, ſent them word that he approved their intentions, and that he would give orders to the Governour of <hi>Lucern</hi> to do them all that honour, and to ſhew them all the reſpect that is due to their Character.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors being entred into the Vallies, acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the Comminalty with their Arrival, who diſpacth'd immediately two Deputies, and two Miniſters to them, to whom they repreſented: That they had employed all their utmoſt endeavours to make the Edict of the 31ſt day of <hi>January</hi> to be revoked, but that all their Reaſons and Inſtances had been unſucceſsful: That it had been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to underſtand that his Royal Highneſs was ſo much engaged with one of the moſt powerful Monarchs of the whole Univerſe: That it was impoſſible for him to break it: And that he was reſolved to do all his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to unite his Subjects in the ſame Religion as he had promiſed him.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98823:15"/>
            <p>Therefore there were no hopes left of obtaining the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking the Orders that had been given againſt them. That their Sovereign Lords had commanded them that in caſe his Royal Highneſs ſhould perſiſt in his reſolution to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his Edict, they ſhould demand his permiſſion to give them leave to retreat out of his Territories, and to diſpoſe of their goods; But that they had not been willing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into any Negotiation upon this Article, without being firſt informed about their intentions about it. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhould aſſemble to deliberate ſeriouſly about ſo important a buſineſs, and to acquaint them afterwards with what they deſired of them in the preſent Junctures.</p>
            <p>The Deputies and Miniſters having conference together about this Propoſition, before they reſolved upon any thing, they pray'd the Ambaſſadors to aſſiſt them with their wiſe Advice and prudent Council. But the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors did refuſe to adviſe them in ſo intricate a buſineſs, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them they were better acquainted with their own For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; with the ſcituation of the Places where they did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to retrench themſelves; with their Ammunitition and Proviſions, than thoſe to whom they did addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to know their Sentiments, and that therefore they themſelves could take the beſt meaſures about it.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, not being able to defend themſelves againſt their ardent deſires, and thinking that they were obliged In charity to aſſiſt them in ſo ſlippery a paſſage, they at laſt granted them their deſires,</p>
            <p>But to be able to adviſe them with a full cogniſance of the cauſes, they did inform themſelves exacty of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that were able to bear Arms in the Valies, of the experience, vallour and conduct of their Officers, of their paſſages of, and avennues to their Countrey, of their Ammunition, and of the quality and goodneſs of their Arms: they asked them above all, if the Inhabitants of the Vallies were well united, and having been informed that they all were not above 2500 fighting men, that there were amongſt them more than 12000 mouths, only fit to conſume; that in ſome places Proviſions begun already to fall ſhort; that the Troops of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> had ſhut up all the Paſſages through which they might expect
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98823:16"/> Recruits: that they had no hopes of any Succours; that it was not very difficult either to ſtarve them, or to reduce them by force of Arms; that they could not retreat to their Neighbours, as in the precedent War: That the <hi>French</hi> King, who did formerly protect them, was their greateſt Enemy; that with few men they were to defend a large Countrey; that being ſeparated one from another, they could not ſpeedily aſſiſt thoſe ſhould ſtand in need of it; that in the very Vallies there were ſome <hi>Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> that had an eye upon their Actions, and that gave advice to the Court of all their Tranſactions; and which was worſt, that two great Princes were joined to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. They told them, that they were much afraid, that conſidering their condition, they ſhould not be able to reſiſt ſo many Forces that were about to fall upon them, and that it would be more advantagious for them to think of a retreat out of their Countrey, provided leave could be got to ſell their Goods, and to carry along with them what they were able to ſave out of the Shipwrack: that they were not poſitively informed of his Royal Highneſs's intention about it; but notwithſtanding he had refuſed it to the Inhabitants of the Vallies, when they did ask it in the third Petition they preſented to their Prince, after his laſt Edict, yet they were in hopes that it would be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them in conſideration of their Sovereign Lords.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters and Deputies having heard this advice, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Ambaſſadors to grant them leave to conſult toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about it before they gave them their Anſwer; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left them, they did debate about it for three hours, without coming to any reſolution, every Party maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Sentiments with very great heat. Some of them were of an Opinion, that they ought not to leave their Countrey, but on the contrary, they ought to hazard their Lives in maintaining the Privileges had been granted them in ſo authentical a manner; ſaying, It would be the greateſt cowardize imaginable, to forfeit their Courage in a Cauſe wererein the honour of God and their Religion was concerned. They added, that the favour they were to expect, would be of no uſe to thoſe that had nothing to defray the charges of their journey; that indeed they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98823:16"/> might find ſome purchaſers of their Eſtates ſcituate in the Plains, but that no body would be willing to buy thoſe upon the Mountains; that there were no ſecurity for them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their departure; that there might happen ſome change in the Affairs of <hi>Europo</hi> that would render their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition better than it was at preſent; and that perhaps <hi>France,</hi> that did not think they would be capable of the leaſt reſiſtance, finding they did defend themſelves with much vigor, and that they did deſtroy a part of her Troops, might recal the remainder in order to preſerve them for ſome more conſiderable exploits; that they were in expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation both of money and men, that were to be ſent to them by Captain <hi>Janavel;</hi> and that they could never want proviſions for making ſallies, from time to time they could oblige their Neighbours to furniſh them with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Proviſions.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that were of a contrary Opinion, anſwered all their Reaſons in the following manner; That it is true, that both Reaſon and Piety do oblige us to hazard our Lives in the Defence of our Liberty, and the Exerciſe of our Religion, when we have ſome hopes to do it with ſucceſs; but that when the danger is unavoidable, and our Ruin certain, it is Madneſs and Deſpair to precipitate our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and that to take up Arms againſt thoſe, whom it is impoſſible to overcome, what efforts ſoever we are able to make, is to be our own Enemies and Deſtroyers; that they had amongſt them but few Perſons capable of Defence; and that how reſolute and brave ſoever they were, it was viſible they could not very long Reſiſt two Puiſſant Armies that were going to fall upon them from all ſides; that it was to feed our ſelves up with vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, to think that the Juncture of Affairs might change; that we ought to take our meaſures according to the preſent Eſtate of things, and according to what will reaſonably happen; and that good Senſe and Wiſdom did not permit us to ground important Reſolutions upon mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Events; that all <hi>Europe</hi> enjoyed a profound Peace; and that <hi>France</hi> being dreaded by all the States in the World, they had no reaſon to believe that ſhe would be attacked by any Prince, nor that any thing could hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98823:17"/> to oblige her to recal her Troops which were ſent into <hi>Piemont</hi> to employ them ſomewhere elſe, that they ought to make no account of the Succours they were in expectation of; and that ſuppoſe they who had promiſed, ſhould ſend them; yet for every Man they ſhould aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their number with, their Enemies would be able to oppoſe one intire Company; that they could not ſubſiſt very long for want of Proviſions; and that ſuppoſe their Sallies ſhould be ſucceſsful (which was not probable) yet all the Proviſions which by this means they would be able to get, would not be enough to ſubſiſt ſo many Perſons. In fine, they let them ſee, that their Reſiſtance being infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly by their total Ruin, they would deſtroy at the ſame time thoſe Ancient Churches, that had ſubſiſted with ſo much Glory in the midſt of ſo many Perſecutions, and that it would be much better by a prudent Retreat to tranſport this Divine Light into ſome other Country, than to extinguiſh it by a haſty Conduct.</p>
            <p>Concering poor Families, they ſaid. That they ought to oblige thoſe that were provided, to contribute ſomething towards the Charges of their Journey, and concerning the Goods which they could not ſell, that ſo weak a Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhould be no hindrance to them; that their Lives ought to be dearer to them than their Lands, and that it was much better to loſe part of our Eſtate, than to loſe our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters and Deputies finding that they could not agree amongſt themſelves; and that beſides, it was a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could not be decided, but by their Commonalties; told the Ambaſſadors, that the Caſe in queſtion being of the greateſt Importance, they could take no Reſolutions about it, without having firſt Aſſembled all their Commonalties to know their Advice, and promiſed them to bring them to <hi>Turin</hi> their laſt Reſolutions, provided they could get for them Paſs-ports.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors being returned to <hi>Turin,</hi> gave the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> to underſtand, that the People of the Valleys would rather dye upon their Fathers Sepulchres, than to loſe the Spiritual Liberty, and to comply with his Royal Highneſs's Edict; ſupplicating him with all Reſpect
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98823:17"/> due to him, to be pleaſed to mitigate it; that therefore, in caſe his Royal Highneſs would abate nothing in favour of his poor Subjects, things would in all appearance come to a dangerous Extremity; and that the Rigour which he would make uſe of on this occaſion, would cauſe the Ruin of part of his People. To which the Ambaſſadors added, That whereas they were in hopes his Royal Highneſs would in Conſideration of their Sovereigns, moderate the Orders he had given againſt his Subjects of the Valleys; they had taken the Liberty to make them ſome Propoſals that would prevent all thoſe Evils which the Execution of his Edict would be capable to produce; and that in fine, that they might be informed of the Intentions of this People about it, they deſired him to grant Paſs-ports for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties which they were willing to ſend them out of the Valleys. But the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> gave them to underſtand, that his Royal Highneſs had very good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not to grant a Paſs-port to the Deputies of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Valleys and that they might ſend the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of the Embaſſy, who might bring them their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>And accordingly the Secretary was ſent into the Vallyes, with this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>WE do not doubt but that your Deputies have faithfully acquainted you with our Sentiments, that are not grounded according to our Opinion, but upon the Publick Good of your Commonalties; and whereas, ſince our arrival to <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin,</hi> we have been informed there of ſeveral things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that our Apprehenſion for you is juſt; that our Advice are good and profitable; We hope that you will follow our Counſel we have given to your Deputies, being perſwaded that God by his Divine Providence will find out for you a Retreat, where you will find all the neceſſary Supports of Life and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to ſerve him in his Fear, and according to your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and ſince you know, that the preſent State of your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs require a prompt Remedy, and that there is no moment loſt to obtain it from your Prince; We found it very neceſſary to diſpatch immediately our Secretary to acquaint you, that his Royal Highneſs did not find it convenient to grant Paſs-ports for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98823:18"/> your Deputies; therefore we deſire you to ſend us preſently your Reſolution in writing, for fear if you ſhould protract it, our Services would be no more reſpected at Court, and that you would render them unſucceſsful to procure you a free and advantagious Retreat, for which (if you deſire it) we will Addreſs our ſelves to his Royal Highneſs with all poſſible Care and Affection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Commonalties having been Aſſembled, the Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry delivered them the Ambaſſadors Letter; and after the reading of it, he told them, That their Affairs grew daily worſe and worſe; that the Ambaſſador of <hi>France</hi> did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually preſs his Royal Highneſs to execute this Edict; that his Royal Highneſs on his ſide was very impatient of it, either becauſe his Reputation was engaged therein, or by reaſon of the great Expence he was forced to be at to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the Troops that were in his Territories; that ſince it was impoſſible to obtain the revoking the Edict, they ought to think upon the moſt convenient means to prevail with his Royal Highneſs to grant a Moderation, which they were in a Condition to demand. In fine, he deſired them to make Reflection on all the Conſiderations that had been alledged by the Ambaſſadors, and to give their Anſwer in writing.</p>
            <p>After this Repreſentation, the Miniſters and the other Deputies having conſulted together, did agree to Anſwer the Ambaſſadors in the following manner.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE have received the Letters which your Excellencies have done us the Honour to ſend us by the Secretary of your Embaſſy, and have been made ſenſible by him of the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Care your Excellencies have taken to repreſent to his Royal Highneſs, our Sovereign, and his Miniſters of State, all the Reaſons that were moſt capable to maintain us in our Right, as alſo the Anſwers made upon the Reproaches of our Conduct, as well as in general of all the Valleys, as of ſome particular Perſons, for which we cannot but render to your Excellencies, all the moſt humble Thanks which the moſt grateful Perſons can be capable of. In the mean time we have made all poſſible reflections on the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98823:18"/> Subject of your Letter; and on what ſide ſoever we turn our eyes, we find very great and almoſt inſurmountable difficulties, which we have made bold to ſet down in the incloſed Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, which we humbly deſire your Excellencies to take into your wiſe conſideration. We are intirely perſwaded that your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies have no other end but to find ſome ſolid expedients for theſe poor Churches; They cannot but make their humble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that in caſe it be impoſſible to revoke the publiſhed Edict, or to find ſome equitable moderation of it, you would have the Charity to follow theſe other expedients which you will judge moſt proper for the conſervation of thoſe that rely altogether upon your conduct, after having ſurveyed the difficulties which the ſaid Memorial mentions. This is, my Lords, the general ſentiments of thoſe Churches, that will never deſiſt to pray the Divine Majeſty for the proſperity of the ſacred Perſons of your Excellencies, and the happy ſucceſs of your holy Emploiment. Theſe are the Prayers of,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt Humble, moſt Obedient, and moſt Obliged Servants, the Miniſters and Deputies of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Churches of</hi> Piemont.
<list>
                           <item>Siderac Baſtie, <hi>Moderator.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>David Leger, <hi>Adjoint.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Jean Chauvie, <hi>Secretary.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Jean Laurens, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Jean Jahier, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>G. Manelot, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>P. Leydet, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>P. Jahier, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Giraud, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Bertrand, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Jean Manelot.</item>
                           <item>Jacques Peyrot.</item>
                           <item>Jean Baptiſte Roberto.</item>
                           <item>Etienne Gautier.</item>
                           <item>Paul Beax.</item>
                           <item>Jean Pierre Guantan.</item>
                           <item>Daniel Alberan.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Angrogne,</hi>
                        <date>March <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>8/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. 1686.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98823:19"/>
            <p>In their Memorial they did remark in the firſt place, that only the rich Families would be able to provide for their Journies; that the others, how well intentioned ſoever they were, could not do it by reaſon of their poverty; and that ſtaying behind, they would infallibly be forced to change their Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it might happen, that after the principal Perſons were out of the Countrey, the others would be detained under ſome pretence or other, though it was promiſed them to grant them Liberty of doing what they pleaſed, and that after having revoked ſuch Patents as were granted them by the mediation of ſeveral Sovereigns, they would make no bones to break their word with the Ambaſſadors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they would fail ſecretly to obſtruct the ſelling of their goods, forbidding the <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> to buy them; and that after all, they would not be able to ſell thoſe that were ſcituate upon the Mountains, and in barren places, but only thoſe that were in the Plains.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They deſired the Ambaſſadors to demand the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe ſums that were juſtly owing to them, and which they could not ask for, before their departure. As alſo it would pleaſe his Royal Highneſs to prevail with the <hi>French</hi> King to ſell their Eſtates which they had in the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Peronſe,</hi> and to ſue for the payment of what was ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them by the Inhabitants of that Countrey.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They begged for a ſufficient time to ſell their goods, and to find out a retreat, and that in the mean while the Execution of the Edict ſhould be ſuſpended, and leave gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Miniſters to continue their Exerciſe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>In fine, They propoſed to the Ambaſſadors the difficulty they would have to find Horſes and Carriages enough to tranſport them, with their Families and Goods, out of the Countrey, there being at leaſt in the Vallies 15000 Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>This Memorial being delivered to the Ambaſſadors, with a Letter of the Inhabitants of the Vallies, they went to make a viſit to the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and having told him that they were in hopes of perſwading this Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98823:19"/> to abandon their native Countrey, provided they could do it with ſafety and advantage, they deſired him to know of his Royal Highneſs if he was willing to grant leave to his unhappy Subjects to retreat out of his Territories, and in caſe he found him inclined to it, he ſhould deſire him that he would be pleaſed to nominate ſome of his Privy Council, with whom they might agree, about the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of their Retreat, and to remove all difficulties they ſhould meet with.</p>
            <p>While the Ambaſſadors ſtaid for his Royal Highneſs's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, they ſolicited with eagerneſs all his Miniſters of State to engagage them to perſwade him of what they deſired ſhould be granted on this occaſion.</p>
            <p>But their cares did not meet with that ſucceſs they were in expectation of; for His Royal Highneſs ſent them word by the Count of <hi>Marſenas,</hi> That being informed by his Miniſters, that they made their earneſt inſtances to obtain a free retreat in favour of his Subjects of the Vallies, and to regulate with his Miniſters the Article about it he had charged him to give them to underſtand; that this people having dared to take up Arms againſt him at the time that no Troops ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached towards their Countrey, had committed a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand inſolent things, and had dared him with the confidence deſerving the moſt rigorous Puniſhments; and that therefore they were unworthy of the Favour the Ambaſſadors deſired for them; in ſo much the more, that before their arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at Court, they had preſented ſeveral Petitions with a profound Submiſſion to obtain ſome Mitigation of the Edict, and that now they pretended with their Swords in their Hands to revoke it; but nevertheleſs, that they aſſured the Ambaſſadors, that in caſe the Rebels ſhould ſhow ſome Repentance of their paſt Conduct, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves with that Reſpect they did owe him, he was in a Condition to make them ſenſible of the Effects of his Clemency, and to ſhow them how much Regard they had for the Recommendations of the Evangelical Cantons.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors being ſurpriſed with this new Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, anſwered the Count of <hi>Marſenas,</hi> That it ſeemed to them, that his Royal Highneſs could not reaſonably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98823:20"/> of his Subjects, that Submiſſion he had ſpoke of; that in caſe this People did declare, that they had fail'd in what they owed their Sovereign, they would render themſelves Criminals by their own Confeſſion; that therefore, they could not be obliged to make a Declaration of this nature; and that tho they ſhould employ themſelves to perſwade them to it, it would be impoſſible to obtain it, for fear they ſhould blacken themſelves with a Crime they thought themſelves innocent of, and to give way to a Confiſcation of their Goods, that they might render themſelves ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by them, in making them ſuch a Propoſition; and that ſuch an Overture would produce no other Effect, but to protract the time of their Negotiation, and indeed to render it fruitleſs.</p>
            <p>But whereas the Count of <hi>Merſenas</hi> ſhowed, That his Royal Highneſs abſolutely expected, that the Submiſſion of the Inhabitants of the Valleys ſhould precede the Favour he would do them; the Ambaſſadors judged, that they ought to apply themſelves to the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe his Royal Highneſs's mind; therefore having waited on him, they deſired him to repreſent to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the endeavouring to oblige his Subjects to confeſs themſelves guilty of Rebellion, He deſired a thing of them they could not grant; that a Declaration of this nature would cover them with Eternal Infamy; that indeed, with a good Conſcience they could not confeſs a Crime they were innocent of; and that at laſt, his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſeemed to make but little Reflections upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Interceſſion of their Sovereigns; deſiring, that the Favours he was asked for, ſhould be the Condition of a Submiſſion, to which his Subjects could not conform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> gave them the ſame Anſwer they received from the Count of <hi>Merſenas,</hi> That the Prince was inexorable upon this Article, and that it was impoſſible to prevail in the leaſt, with his mind, what Reaſon ſoever they could alledg; and that therefore it was in vain to endeavour to make time change his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98823:20"/>
            <p>The Anſwer of the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> troubled very much the Ambaſſadors, who were afraid that this was a ſtumbling block prepar'd for the Inhabitant of the Valleys; and that there was a Deſign laid to condemn them upon their own Confeſſion of their Rebellion. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs they thought that this difficulty ought not to oblige them to break the Treaty which they had entred upon; they conſider'd that the Prince might publiſh in the World, That his Subjects had ſcorned to accept of his Favours. Beſides, they conſidered, that the ill ſucceſs of this Negotiation might be imputed to them; but the greateſt reaſon that confirmed them in this deſign, was, that they found that it would be more advantagious to the Inhabitants of the Valleys to ſhew this compliance with their Soveraign's Will, than to expoſe themſelves to all the Miſeries their Diſobedience might draw upon them; it was for this reaſon that they reſolved to conſent to the Accommodation was offered them, it being a leſſer Evil, than to ſee the Churches of the Valleys deſolate; and the rather, that the Marqueſs of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> did aſſure them, That his Royal Highneſs, to mark the Eſteem he had for them, would grant upon their Interceſſion, all that he could reaſonably be asked for, without wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Reputation.</p>
            <p>But before they did propoſe to the inhabitants of the Valleys what their Prince expected from them, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors did deſire not only to be informed of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Submiſſion which they would oblige them to, but alſo to regulate the Form and the Terms of it, with the Miniſters of his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>Therefore having made on both ſides ſeveral Projects of the Petition which his Royal Highneſs was to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with, by his Subjects of the Valleys, it was at laſt agreed that it ſhould contain a very humble Supplication, by which they were to deſire the Prince to pardon their Offences, and to be perſwaded, that if they had failed in their Reſpect which they owed him, yet that they were not come ſhort of that Fidelity which could be expected from dutiful Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98823:21"/>
            <p>After which the Ambaſſadours having got Paſsports for five or ſix of the Inhabitants of the Vallies, they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch'd to them the Secretary of the Embaſſy, with this following Letter:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ACcording to your Intention which you acquainted us with in your Letter of the 28th of <hi>March,</hi> and the incloſed Memorial, we have deſired of his Royal Highneſs, That he would be pleaſed to grant you leave to retreat out of his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and to diſpoſe of all your Goods; and to that purpoſe to give us ſome Commiſſioners with Power to regulate the manner of your Retreat: Whereof his Royal Highneſs has given us to underſtand by one of his Miniſters, That being your Soveraign, he could not, without making a breach into his Honour and Authority, enter into a Treaty with you; but that it was requiſite you ſhould ſend him five or ſix Perſons, with full Power to make him that Submiſſion which you owe him; and to ask by a Petition, what Favour you deſire ſhould be granted to you; and that afterwards he will let you ſee the Conſiderations he has for our Soveraignty. It is true, that we expected a more favourable Anſwer than this; but nevertheleſs, to take away all pretences his Royal Righneſs could take hold on, to make ſuch Deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that might be fatal to you, we think you will do well to ſend your Deputies hither as ſoon as is poſſible, promiſing you, that we will aſſiſt them with our Counſels in the delivering their Petition. Our Secretary is to deliver you this Letter, with the incloſed Paſsports, which will acquaint you more at length with the particulars of our Negotiation, and with the diſpoſition of the Court in your regard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Secretary of the Embaſſy having delivered this Letter to the Deputies of the Valleys which he had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, and given them an exact Account of all the Negotiation of the Ambaſſadors, and of the effect it had produced; made them a long Speech, to exhort them to a compliance with their Prince's Will, and deſire
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98823:21"/> them to diſpatch him with all ſpeed, aſſuring them that in conſideration of the Ambaſſadors, they would obtain much more favours then they did expect.</p>
            <p>The moſt ſenſible and moſt reaſonable Perſons of this Aſſembly, and above all the Miniſters, imployed their utmoſt endeavours to oblige the others to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Law which they would impoſe upon them; becauſe in that extremity which they were reduced unto, they muſt either periſh with their miſerable Families, or do what was deſired of them.</p>
            <p>But all thoſe Reaſons which they could alledge, were not capable to perſwade them; inſomuch, that after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving debated the Queſtion, and conſulted together about it almoſt a whole day, they did diſſolve themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being able to agree in the ſame Opinion. Thoſe of the Valleys of St. <hi>Martyn,</hi> of <hi>Pezonſe,</hi> of St. <hi>Bartholemew,</hi> of <hi>Pazuſtin,</hi> of <hi>Rocheplate,</hi> of <hi>Villard,</hi> and of <hi>Rozas,</hi> and ſome of <hi>La Tour</hi> were of Opinion to make thoſe Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which were deſired of them; and having nominated ſome to this purpoſe, with Order to part for <hi>Turin,</hi> they charged them with Procurations in good form, by which they promiſed to execute all the Ambaſſador ſhould find convenient in the Negotiation which they were entred upon for the Intereſt of the Churches of the Valleys. But thoſe of <hi>Bobys,</hi> of St. <hi>John,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering themſelves with hopes of imaginary Succours, did reſolve to defend the Exerciſe of their Religion with their Arms in their Hands, and ſent to the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours their Deputy named <hi>Blanchy,</hi> who delivered them this following Letter:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98823:22"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt High, Mighty, and Soveraign Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IN follow of the Letter, your Excellencies have been pleaſed to write to thoſe Valleys ſome few days ago, our Churches of St. <hi>Jean, Angrogne,</hi> and <hi>Boby,</hi> throw themſelves at your Feet, to aſſure you of their humble Reſpect, and of their due acknowledgments of the Favours your Excellencies endeavours to obtain for them, from his Royal Highneſs, our Soveraign, concerning the Continuation of the Exerciſe of our Religion in theſe places. And concerning the Propoſals that are now on foot, having been uncapable of perſwading our People to the ſame Sentiments, which the other Churches have, in order to comply with your Excellencies Demands, we have charg'd our Deputy, Mr. <hi>Daniel Blanchis, Syndicus</hi> of the Communalty of St. <hi>Jean,</hi> to acquaint you by word of mouth, of our true Sentiments. And we humbly beſeech you, that you would be pleaſed to continue the effects of your inexprimable and Fatherly Charity, and principally in regard of your powerful Interceſſions by his Royal Highneſs, about the above-mentioned Subject: Beſeeching the Lord to bleſs your Negotiation, and to be your abundant Rewarder of all the Cares, Pains, and Troubles your Excellencies have the goodneſs to take for our poor Flocks, in the Name of which we make it always our Glory to carry with all Reſpect and Submiſſion imaginable, the Title of your Excellencies most humble, most obedient, and much obliged Servants, the Deputies of the following Churches,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <list>
                                    <head>
                                       <hi>Deputies of the Church of St.</hi> Jean.</head>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Michael Puriſe</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Jean Muſton</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Jean Putta,</hi> for <hi>Angrogne.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <list>
                                    <head>
                                       <hi>Of the Church of</hi> Boby.</head>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Marque de Daniel </hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Negrin N.</hi> Syndicus</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Franc. Dane,</hi> Counſellor</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Stephen Pertin,</hi> Deputy</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Angrogne</hi>
                           <date>April the 4th, <hi>1686.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98823:22"/>
            <p>The Sieur <hi>De la Baſtie,</hi> Miniſter at St. <hi>Jean,</hi> touch'd by the Diviſions of theſe poor Churches, writ to the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours in theſe following Terms:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Take the liberty to render your Excellencies my moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reſpects, by the Deputies that go to <hi>Turin,</hi> to make their Submiſſion to his Royal Highneſs, and to preſent him ſuch a Petition as your Excellencies will think fit. I and my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are in the greateſt conſternation and affliction in the world to ſee our People ſo much divided about a Retreat, apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Diviſions will ſpoil your Excellencies charitable Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation with his Royal Highneſs in our behalf, and render their Cares and Troubles unſucceſsful. We have employed our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours to make them ſenſible, that conſidering the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Junctures of Affairs, it was the beſt Reſolution they could take, but we have not been happy enough to have like ſucceſs with all. If we were not ſatisfied of your Excellencies incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable Charity we ſhould have reaſon to fear that this indiſcreet Conduct would much change their goodneſs and zeal for our Interest. We moſt humbly beſeech your Excellencies to make uſe on this occaſion of your Goodneſs and Clemency, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in your infatigable Cares for theſe poor Churches. I moſt humbly beg your Excellencies Pardon for my boldneſs, and beſeech you to give me leave to render you my moſt humble Reſpects, and to aſſure you, that I am with all the Reſpect and Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion imaginable,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Excellencies moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt obliged Servant,</hi> Sidrac Baſtie, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>Angrogne,
<date>April <hi>4. 1686.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>This diverſity of Opinion made the Ambaſſadours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, that the Enemies of their Religion taking hold of the diviſion of the Inhabitants of the Valleys might prevail with his Royal Highneſs to confound the Innocent with the Guilty, and to refuſe all a Retreat out of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98823:23"/>
            <p>Therefore they ſent back into the Valleys the Deputy of <hi>Boby,</hi> with a Letter to thoſe that were reſolved to take up Arms; and they did conjure him to employ his utmoſt endeavours to make them agree with the other Churches. The Letter was writ in this following man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IT is true that ones native Soil has great charms, and that most Men have a natural deſire to live and to die there: Yet the Children of God ought not to ſet their hearts thereupon, becauſe they are Foreigners upon Earth, and Heaven is their true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country; therefore you will be guilty of miſtrust to God's providence, if you fancy you cannot find any other Country where you may live conveniently, and adore your heavenly Father. In what part of the World ſoever we ourſelves be tranſported, we ought to think ourſelves happy, provided we have there freedom to ſerve God according to our conſciences: You ought to propoſe to yourſelves the examples of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, who have drawn upon them God's bleſſing by truſting to his promiſes, and by abandoning their houſes and fields, to go to inhabite ſome remote Country. A confidence of this nature, cannot but be very acceptable to the Lord; and it is without doubt more agreeable with the Spirit of the Goſpel, than to take up Arms against your Soveraign; it is to Sufferings Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are call'd too, and not to a Reſiſtance: And we do not find that either the Apoſtles or the Primitive Church, made uſe of any other Weapons against their Perſecutors, but Prayers and Patience. Theſe are the Conſiderations that have obliged our Soveraign Lords the Evangelical Cantons, to give us or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of procuring for you from his Royal Highneſs, your lawful Prince, a free Retreat, with permiſſion to diſpoſe of your Goods, in caſe he would no longer grant you the Exerciſe of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and tho' you look upon this Retreat as an inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Unhappineſs, yet they do nevertheleſs conſider it as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, reflecting according to their great wiſdom, upon the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition you are reduced to; and indeed they did think
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98823:23"/> it would be very hard to obtain it from his Royal Highneſs, and that in caſe he did grant it upon their request, you ought not only to accept it with ſubmiſſion, but to ſhew your great acknowledgement for it: Whereafter you will not doubt that we have been ſurprized to hear that you make difficulty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve yourſelves to it, and that you have a deſign to reſist two powerful Princes that are reſolved to extirpate you, in caſe you make the least oppoſition; for by this behaviour you do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly act against your Duty, against Chriſtian Prudence, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your true Interest, but you give us alſo just reaſons to complain of you, that having engaged us into a Negotiation with your Prince, you will not take hold of thoſe advant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages we are in a condition to procure you: Open therefore your eyes, and conſider the misfortunes you draw upon yourſelves, and the fatal conſequences of your deſign, that must needs turn to the entire deſtruction of your Churches and Families. Conſider, that what is offer'd you, is ſo advantageous, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the preſent ſtate of your Affairs, that ſeveral perſons of the greatest Quality, would have accepted of it as the greatest Happineſs, in the late Perſecutions of <hi>France,</hi> and that they would have been exceedingly joyful to get ſtark na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out of their Country without hindrance: If you do make Reflections upon all theſe things, we are in hopes that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of thoſe that are of a better opinion, will touch and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to follow the ſame Conduct; but if you refuſe to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate it, and if you perſist in your obſtinacy, you will be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before God, not only of having thrown away your lives, which you might have ſaved, and of having expoſed your Wives and your Children to the Maſſacre, but alſo of having cauſed the ruine of theſe noble Remains of the <hi>Vaudois</hi> Churches, which you might have tranſported into ſome other Country. And do not flatter yourſelves of being capable to prevent theſe Evils by the means of ſome Succours that ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have promiſed you, for we do aſſure you, that thoſe that entertain you with theſe vain imaginations do abuſe you, and that you cannot be aſſiſted from any ſide: You ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that you will be left by all Men, and by ſome of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Inhabitants of your Country, and that therefore you will
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98823:24"/> ſoon be deſtroyed, either by the Sword or by Famine, and that thoſe that may eſcape the fury of their Enemies, will finiſh their Lives either by being burnt at the Stake, upon the Rack, or the Gallows: We conjure you, that you would be prevailed with by ſo powerful conſiderations, and to agree with the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of the Commonalty, that are reſolved to deſire of their Prince a permiſſion to retreat out of his Territories, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Divine Providence will conduct you to ſome places where you will perhaps find more advantageous eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then thoſe you leave behind you; and where thoſe that are poor will not be in want of charitable perſons that will provide them with all neceſſaries. In expectation that God will inſpire you with good reſolutions, and that you will give to your Deputy ſuch a Procuration as thoſe of the other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalties have given, we recommend you to his Mercy and his Divine Protection, reſting, Gentlemen, your very Affectionate to render you Service.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Turin,</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>April.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Expecting the return of this Deputy, the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors thought fit to acquaint the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> with the diſpoſition of the Inhabitants of the Vallies, and to endeavour to prevent the evils their Diviſion might draw upon them, as well from his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as ſome of their Enemies in his Privy Counſel. Then they went to pay this Miniſter a Viſit, and told him, that the Deputies were arrived, that five of them were ready to make in the name of their Commonalties the Submiſſion his Royal Highneſs deſired of them, but that ſome others, who not knowing what they were to expect from the goodneſs of his Royal Highneſs, were not yet reſolved to do it; that in the mean time they were admoniſhed by Letter to follow the ſentiments of theſe that had a deſire to ſubmit themſelves to his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs; and that in a ſhort time their Reſolutions would be known.</p>
            <p>He was afterwards deſired to intercede in favour of this poor People with his Royal Highneſs, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98823:24"/> him to have ſome indulgence for them; That whereas they were prepoſſeſſed with ſome diſtruſt, he would be pleaſed to clear their Doubts, ſo that their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion might be made by an unanimous accord, to the ſatisfaction of the Prince and his Subjects.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> ſeemed to be ſurprized with the obſtinacy of the People of the Valleys; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, he gave ſome hopes that he would imploy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Royal Highneſs to prevent that their delay, to give him the ſatisfaction he expected, ſhould not be prejudicial to them, and that at laſt the Prince did not reſolve to follow the Counſel of thoſe that were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally perſwading him to rigour.</p>
            <p>In the mean time whereas the Court ſeemed to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to ſee the end of this Affair, the Ambaſſadours writ a Letter to the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas,</hi> to give him to underſtand that they had made a project of a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the Inhabitants of the Valleys, which they were ready to deliver, if it could be ſigned by the Deputies; but whereas one of them was abſent, they deſired him to put off all things till his return.</p>
            <p>The day after this Letter had been delivered to the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas,</hi> the Ambaſſadours went to him to know the effect which it had produced; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he was very eager to oblige the five Deputies, who were then at <hi>Turin,</hi> to ſign the Petition which he had found in a good form; it was declared to him, that the Subſcription could not be made in the abſence of him that was ſent into the Valleys; that being joyned by intereſt, they could not ſeparate themſelves one from another, and that in fine, it was agreed, that the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be ſigned by all the Deputies at one time. But whereas the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> had ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Orders to haſten a Subſcription of thoſe Deputies that were then at Court; he ſeemed not to be ſatisfied with the reaſons that were given him for the refuſing what he deſired; and the next day after he ſent one of his Servants to deſire the Ambaſſadours to prevail with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98823:25"/> the Deputies to give him that ſatisfaction he deſired. But the Ambaſſadours writ him a Letter, by which they gave him to underſtand, that it was not juſt to ſeparate in the Subſcription thoſe that were ingaged in the ſame Cauſe, that in caſe ſome did ſign without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſuch proceedings could not but have troubleſome conſequences; and that therefore they did conjure him to expect one day longer the return of the ſixth Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to prevaile with his Royal Highneſs to grant this little delay upon their requeſt.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs having received this Letter, told the Secretary of the Ambaſſy, that was the Deliverer of it, That his Royal Highneſs was extreamly tired with theſe delays, and that he was much afraid he ſhould take ſome reſolutions that would carry things to a fatal extremity; and that therefore it was neceſſary to oblige the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſign immediately their Petition, and to carry it to him in order to be preſented to his Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>The Deputies fearing to offend ſo powerful a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, in caſe they refuſed to appear before him, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to go to his Houſe, but what inſtance ſoever he could make to perſwade them to ſign the Petition; and for all he did aſſure them, that it ſhould be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to thoſe of <hi>Boby,</hi> yet they perſiſted in their firſt deſign, excuſing themſelves by reaſon of being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to expect a return of the Deputy that was gone into the Valleys, by the incertitude of the ſucceſs of his Negotiation, by the ſhortneſs of time for his return, and in fine, by the danger ſuch a proceeding might draw upon them.</p>
            <p>The diſpoſitions of theſe Deputies, and of thoſe of the Inhabitants of the Valleys, that were reſolved to take up Arms, gave great diſturbance to his Royal Highneſs, and that which augmented his diſpleaſure was the news he received that they had killed two <hi>French</hi> Men belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Cittadel of <hi>Pignerol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ambaſſador of <hi>France</hi> that was much offended with his Royal Highneſs's delay to execute his Edict, did
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98823:25"/> not fail to take hold on this accident, in order to diſpoſe the Prince to revenge himſelf of this crime, that was committed by his Subjects in deſpite of his Authority, and to perſwade him to keep no longer any meaſures with thoſe people whom he was pleas'd to ſtile Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels.</p>
            <p>In the mean while that their Enemies were buſie to their deſtruction, their Deputies were at <hi>Turine</hi> in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition, and not knowing what reſolution to take, they deſired the Ambaſſadors advice how they ſhould behave themſelves in this great extremity.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors being in hopes that the Deputy who was gone to <hi>Boby</hi> would return in a ſhort time, and that they might acquaint them with things capable to appeaſe his Royal Highneſs's mind, thought fit to wait for his arrival before they ſhould take any reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>But whereas the Deputy was waited for a long time, that his Royal Highneſs was continually ſollicited by the Ambaſſadour of <hi>France,</hi> to put a concluſion to this buſineſs, that beſides the Troops that were in his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories did put him to very great charges, and the Prince was informed that the Ambaſſadors had diſpatched an Expreſs into <hi>Switzerland</hi> that might bring them ſome new Inſtructions; all theſe reaſons did oblige him to end this Affair, inſomuch, that how preſſing and urgent ſoever the inſtances of the Ambaſſadors were, in favour of the Inhabitants of the Valleys, to perſwade the Prince ſtill to put off for a little while, he publiſhed the 9th of <hi>June</hi> this following Edict:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>THe Divine Providence eſtabliſhing Soveraigns above the People, has given to the first the diſtribution of favours and puniſhments, that the hopes of the one might make the Good mindful of their duty, and that the ſence of the other might prevent the Bad to abandon themſelves to evil: This latter ought to fall from Our avenging-hands upon our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> making profeſſion of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98823:26"/> Reformed Religion, becauſe it is notorious that they have not only gain-ſaid with great obſtinacy, our Order of the 31st of <hi>January</hi> last, but that they have alſo hardned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Crime, and are fallen into an inormous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumated Rebellion; Nevertheleſs our natural clemency ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their crime, and not contenting ourſelves with our Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kindneſs, with which we have ſo long time unſucceſsfully waited for their repentance, we have ſtill been willing to leave to their will (which has ever followed bad Counſels) the choice of a good or miſerable Condition, and to open them at the last tryal, the gates of our favour, that ſo they may be able to take hold of it in the following manner, and that in caſe they ſhould not anſwer it by a ready obedience, they might not be able to impute but to their own raſhneſs, their deſerved puniſhments, which we ſhall inflict upon them without delay.</p>
                     <p>Therefore confirming in the first place our Order of the 31st of <hi>January</hi> last, as far as it ſhall not be found contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this, we have by vertue of this preſent Edict, with our certain knowledge, full power and abſolute authority, and with advice of our Privy-Councel, commanded all our Subjects of the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> making profeſſion of the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, to lay down their Arms, and to retire into their Houſes within the term hereafter preſcribed.</p>
                     <p>We command them alſo to make no more any Aſſociations, nor to hold any Conventicles, that ſo according to our intention the Judges of the place may have a free acceſs, and that the Miſſionaries and other Religious Perſons may return to the Churches which they have been forced to leave, and that the Catholicks, and thoſe which have imbraced the Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, may return to their Houſes which they have abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                     <p>And whereas it is not reaſonable that the Religious Miſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the Catholicks, and thoſe which have imbraced the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, ſhould be at a loſs by occaſion of ſeveral dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages which they have received from thoſe of the pretended Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, we deſire, command, and ordain, that all the neceſſary ſums to endemnifie them be generally and withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> diſtinction be reprized upon the Goods of thoſe of the pretended
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98823:26"/> Reformed Religion, ſo as it ſhall be ſummary juſtified before the Chevalier <hi>Monzonx,</hi> Intendant of Juſtice of the Valleys, declaring, nevertheleſs, that in caſe thoſe of the ſaid Religion prove that the damages have been cauſed by ſome particular perſons, they may have their Recourſe and Warrant against them.</p>
                     <p>And to ſhew our ſaid Subjects how great our clemency is towards them, we grant leave to thoſe that ſhall think of a retreat out of our Territories, to do it within the term, and upon the conditions hereafter preſcribed: But becauſe their ill will has ſhewed itſelf but too much by their past conduct, and that ſeveral could hide their evil deſigns under a falſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of obedience, we reſerve for ourſelves, beſides thoſe who ſhall retreat out of our Territories upon their own motion, to ordain it alſo to ſuch we ſhall think fit, and as we ſhall find it moſt expedient to ſecure the peace of thoſe that ſhall ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, whence we do intend to preſcribe the Rules which they ſhall obſerve for the future.</p>
                     <p>And for an augmentation of our favours, we grant leave as well to thoſe that ſhall voluntarily retreat, as to thoſe who retreat by our orders, to take along with them their Goods and Effects at their pleaſure, and to ſell thoſe they ſhall leave behind them, provided they do it in ſuch a manner as is hereafter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
                     <p>The ſame is to be underſtood concerning Strangers, and thoſe that are born from Strangers, who are to conform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to all but the last Article of our Order of the 31st of <hi>January</hi> last, here above mentioned.</p>
                     <p>The ſaid ſelling of Goods ſhall be made to Catholicks, or to perſons that have embraced the Catholick Religion; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there may perhaps not be found Buyers within the term here-before preſcribed, and that we are not willing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat the Zealots of that Religion, who ſhall retreat out of our Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, ſhould be deprived of the benefits of our preſent conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they may agree about, or ſix perſons into whoſe hands they ſhall put their Procurations, who ſhall have leave to ſtay during three months in <hi>Lucerne,</hi> with full liberty to treat and nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate with whom they think fit to ſell the Goods of thoſe who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98823:27"/> ſhall have retreated, and who ſhall have leave to preſcribe in their Procurations the Conditions of their ſelling their Goods for their better ſecurity, to receive the Price thereof in what place ſoever they deſire it ſhould be ſent them, without fraud and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, of the conſtituted Procurators, which the Chevalier and Intendant <hi>Monzonx</hi> ſhall take care of.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe that ſhall be willing to retreat, ſhall be obliged to meet at the Day and Place hereafter ſpecified to be ready to depart without Fire-Arms by the way, that ſhall be named them, either through <hi>Savoy,</hi> or the <hi>Val d'Aſte;</hi> to this purpoſe, we will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them with Paſsports, that they may receive no ill uſage or hinderance in our Territories; but that on the contrary, they may find all poſſible aſſiſtance; and becauſe that being in great number they may be expoſed to ſome Inconveniences upon the way, and in the Places through which they are to go overcharged, they ſhall divide themſelves into three Bodies as is herein before-mentioned: The first ſhall be compoſed of thoſe of the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> ſhall meet at <hi>Tour</hi> this Month of <hi>April;</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, compoſed of thoſe of the Valleys of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholemew, Rocheplatte,</hi> and <hi>Paruſtine,</hi> ſhall meet at St. <hi>Second,</hi> and ſhall part the day following, <hi>viz.</hi> the Twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of this Month; the Third and Last made up by thoſe of the Valleys of St. <hi>Martyn</hi> and <hi>Peronſe,</hi> ſhall meet at <hi>Mica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole,</hi> and part from thence the Third Day, <hi>viz.</hi> the Twenty third of this Month.</p>
                     <p>The term wherein our ſaid Subjects of the pretended Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion, that inhabit the Valleys of <hi>Lucerne,</hi> ſhall be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to lay down their Arms, in the manner preſcribed in the First Article of this preſent Order, That within Eight Days after the Publication hereof in <hi>Lucerne,</hi> during which they ought to have obeyed the Contents of the ſaid Order, to enjoy the fruits of our Clemency, by which as well as our Fatherly Affection towards our ſaid Subjects, we leave to its nature and courſe, notwithſtanding the enormity of their Crimes. And by means of a punctual obſervation of all herein contained, we grant our Favour, Pardon, Remiſſion, Abolition, and a full Amneſty to our ſaid Subjects of all their Exceſſes, Miſdemeanors, Crimes, and other things which they may have committed ſince the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98823:27"/> of our Order of the Thirty First of <hi>January</hi> last, as well in general as particular, ſo that they may not be called to an Account, for under what pretence whatſoever, prohibiting all Judges, Fiſcals, and others whom it belongs to, to enquire into it. But becauſe in caſe they ſhould render themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of ſuch Favours, by not obſerving all that is here above-mentioned, within the preſcribed term, it would be too perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious an Example to delay any longer their deſerved Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, after having been prodigal to them of our Favours, and after having waited ſo long time for their Repentance, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make uſe of thoſe means which God has put into our hands to bring the Obſtinate to their Duty, and to make them feel the Puniſhments of their great preſumption, commanding our Senate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline> 
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Turin,
<date>
                              <hi>the 9th of</hi> April, <hi>1686.</hi>
                           </date> Inrolled
<date>the 10th.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſoon as the Edict was Printed, the Mayor of St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> brought a Copy of it to the Ambaſſador's, whom he would make believe, that it was only on their account, that his Royal Highneſs expreſſed ſo much kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Subjects, and that notwithſtanding the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of <hi>France</hi> was very angry, that there was ſo much condeſcenſion made in favour of the Valleys; that nevertheleſs he was willing to ſee the Edict faithfully exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors having read it immediately in the Marqueſs's preſence, made ſome Reflections upon it, and principally were not ſatisfied with the ſhortneſs of time that was granted to thoſe unhappy People to retreat out of his Royal Highneſs's Territories, and to diſpoſe of their Goods, with the little number of Procurators that were charged to ſell the Goods of ſo great a number of Perſons, with the time in which the Goods were to be ſold; and with ſome other Difficulties which they met with in the Exemption of this Edict, and which they reſolved to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to his Royal Highneſs, after having ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Ambaſſador had left the Marqueſs, they ſent for the Deputies of the Valleys, that were ready to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98823:28"/> make the Submiſſion, and obliged them to return home, deſiring them to acquaint their Commonalties with all that had paſſed; as alſo with the Contents of the Edict, and to aſſure them, That unleſs they did ſubmit, it would be impoſſible to obtain the leaſt mitigation in the execution of thoſe things therein contained.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the ſixth Deputy, who had been ſo long time expected returned out of the Valleys, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Ambaſſadors, That the Commonalties that had made a deſign to defend themſelves, did perſiſt in the ſame Reſolution; and that all he did alledge to make them enter into a better Opinion, had no effect upon their minds; as it was evident by the Letters which were ſent them out of the Valleys in the following manner:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE did not fail immediately after the arrival of our Deputy, to make ſome Copies of the Letter which your Excellencies have been pleaſed to write to our Churches, and they have been read every where after Sermon, there can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be ſaid that is either more true, or more moving and comforting; and your Excellencies may be fully perſwaded, that there is no body but that finds, and does acknowledge that it is the effect of your holy and Chriſtian Charity towards our Churches; yet notwithſtanding it has been till now abſolutely impoſſible to diſpoſe our People to a Retreat out of this Country; ſome out of fear it might cauſe the loſs of ſeveral Perſons that ſhall venture to ſtay behind; others by a principle of Conſcience, and others out of ſeveral other Conſiderations, which our Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will tell your Excellencies by word of mouth. We are in the greateſt conſternation about it, and dare not almost appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Excellencies with ſo much irreſolution: Our People ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here the more to their Opinion, becauſe they have been acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſeveral other Churches, at least a great part of thoſe that compoſed them, did not know that the buſineſs was about ſuch a Retreat, when they gave their Procuration to their Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or if they had underſtood them, they had changed their minds, which give us just reaſon to fear, that in caſe your Excellencies ſhould be farther engaged for this People, you would
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98823:28"/> be extreamly diſpleaſed with their refuſal to Retreat; and it was by reaſon of this fear we had here the last <hi>Sunday,</hi> when we deſired your Excellencies to give us leave to inform our ſelves of the minds of our People about this Propoſition, fore-ſeeing at the ſame time that it would be very hard to perſwade them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> they were for the moſt part reſolved to be their Father's Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and hope that the Lord will be their Deliverer, that would make uſe of feeble things to confound the ſtrong, and that Heaven would find out ſome hinderance to thoſe Deſigns which are formed againſt us. We do not queſtion but this extreamly afflicts your Excellencies; and we are touched with it to our very Souls: but it is not in our power to change their Hearts, and to diſpoſe of other Mens Will; nevertheleſs we conjure your Excellencies in all poſſible humility, that you would not be pleas'd to abate your kindneſs to theſe Churches, neither to deprive us of your powerful and comfortable ſupport, which, under God, has made us ſubſist till now. For God's ſake do always pity us, what way ſoever our Affairs ſhall go, we lay our Souls before God, to ſupplicate him with all ardency, that he would be pleaſed to direct all things to the Glory of his Holy Name, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our People; and that he would grant by his Divine Providence, by the means of your Excellencies, we may ſtill get the prolongation of ſome days, that we may once more inform our ſelves of the Sentiments of our People by the collecting every Man's Voice in particular, if it be poſſible, to know their last Reſolutions; ſo that we may not be blamed, neither of one ſide or another. The Lord be the abundant Rewarder of your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies Charities, and we are with all manner of Reſpect,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Excellencies moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt obliged Servants,</hi> The Deputies of <hi>Boby,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Angrogne.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <list>
                                    <head>
                                       <hi>Deputies of</hi> Boby,</head>
                                    <item>John Aghitto,</item>
                                    <item> Daniel Graffe,</item>
                                    <item> Eſtiennor Danno,</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <list>
                                    <head>
                                       <hi>Deputies of St.</hi> John.</head>
                                    <item> Michael Pariſa,</item>
                                    <item> John Muſchon, </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <list>
                                    <head>
                                       <hi>Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of</hi> Angrogne.</head>
                                    <item> John Duffa,</item>
                                    <item> Piezze Duffa,</item>
                                    <item> Lewis Odin, </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>Angrogne,
<date>Apr. <hi>9. 1686.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98823:29"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt High, Mighty, and Soveraign Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE throw our ſelves in all humility to your Excellenties Feet, to ſhew you our most ſenſible and inexpreſſible diſpleaſure that the great part of our People are not capable to conſider with a Chriſtian prudence the Favour your Excellencies endeavour to procure them, by a free Retreat out of this Country, with Body and Goods, and to embrace it with a holy Joy, as a Preſent from Heaven, and a Grace which they have ſighed for at other times; this makes our Hearts bleed, and ſo much the more, that your Excellencies Letter which you have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to write to them, ſhould have immediately diſpoſed them to an Affair of this nature; yet we dare ſtill moſt humbly beſeech your Excellencies to have the goodneſs to paſs a love on all theſe Conſiderations, as knowing very well that one has to do with the Rabble, it is very hard to compaſs them, and to make them all ſenſible of the reaſon, and the ſtate of Things, but by the length of time, and principally when it is aboue abandoning there ſo old, and ſo dear preſerved native Soyl: there are, nevertheleſs, a great many, and the moſt principal of them, that reſign themſelves intirely to your Excellencies Counſel, Charity, and Prudence, and that will never oppoſe what you will find most expedient for the Glory of God, and their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and preſervation. The Miniſters alſo are all of the ſame Opinion, and we are all willing punctually to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Counſel your Excellencies will be pleaſed to give us. And we moſt humbly beſeech you to pitty us and our Families, to draw us out of a Misfortune which in all appearance is una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable; this is the Favour we hope from your Excellencies, and pray the Lord to bleſs your Lordſhips with all manner of proſperity; and we are with all poſſible reſpect and ſubmiſſion, moſt High, Mighty, and Soveraign Lord,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your Excellencies moſt humble, and moſt obedient Servants,</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Sidrac Baſtie, </item>
                              <item>Guillaume Mallanot.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Angrogne, Apr. <hi>9. 1686.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <list>
                           <item>I. <hi>We have been informed for certain, by a good hand, that his Royal Highneſs will not grant us a Retreat with our Goods,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98823:29"/> but that he pretends to detain them for the Charges he has been at already.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item> II. <hi>That he abſolutely pretends that the Miniſters and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners ſhould be delivered into his hands.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item> III. <hi>That we ſhould lay down our Arms, and that we ſhould deliver them up to the Governour.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item> IV. <hi>That the Troops are to enter into the Valleys to demoliſh the Churches, and to obſtruct all Divine Exerciſe.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item> V. <hi>In fine, we have been informed, that the Council would by no means ſuffer that the</hi> French <hi>Troops ſhould march againſt us.</hi> 
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </postscript>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors had no ſooner read theſe Letters, but they ſent back the Deputy with another Letter, of which were made two Copies, one of them was directed to thoſe of St. <hi>Boby,</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> and the other to thoſe of <hi>Angrogne,</hi> and <hi>La Tour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Letter there was remonſtrated to them the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and little ſolidneſs of their Reaſons they made uſe of not to accept the Favours was offer'd them. It was agreed with them, That the Laws obliging our native Country were very hard; but they were told at the ſame time, that the other Law that obliges us to abandon the Eternal God, and to renounce the true Religion, is ſtill much harder; that we ought to think our ſelves happy, of being able to chooſe between ſuch miſerable Extremities, that it was a Happineſs which was refuſed in <hi>France</hi> to Perſons of the higheſt kank, and of eminent Merits, that were detained by force in their Country, and forced to abandon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Idolatry. That the Affairs of this World were ſubject to perpetual Revolutions; that Kings and Princes are often obliged to abandon their Crowns, and to leave their Seate to their Enemies: and that therefore particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons ought to undergo without murmuring this Common Law, and to reſign themſelves with ſubmiſſion to the Orders of Providence, who puts by her chaſtiſing the ſtate of her Children, to a tryal to divert their Hearts from the World, and to move them to ſearch with ſo much more eagerneſs their heavenly Country; that they had reaſon to believe that the Arm of God that had ſupported
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98823:30"/> them in the Wars paſt was not ſhortned; but they were to conſider that at that time God had raiſed ſome of their Neighbours who did ſupport with their Goods, with their Troops, and their Officers, that then they had none but Friends about them; inſtead of that, now at preſent, they were ſurrounded every where with Enemies; that at that time they had a great many amongſt them capable to bear Arms, that they were united together; but that at preſent they were deprived of all thoſe advantages; that their Soveraign alone was able to extirpate them intirely, and that yet theſe were not the only Troops they were to fight againſt, that thoſe of <hi>France</hi> were ready to fall upon them; and that ſuppoſe they were happy enough to get ſome advantage over them at the firſt Attack, yet at the laſt they would not fail to be oppreſt by the great number of thoſe that would ſucceed thoſe that were vanquiſhed: that beſides their diviſion amongſt themſelves would be very prejudicial to them; that their refuſing to accept their Soveraign's offer would oblige all the Proteſtant Princes to abandon them, becauſe they had rather raſhly take up Arms, than to follow the Counſel was given to them; that they ought not to flatter themſelves with hopes of ſome miraculous deliverance, as was that which God granted to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> by routing the whole Army of <hi>Senacherib;</hi> that in the Age we live in, God makes no Miracles in favour of his Church, as in the time of the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> that the holy Scripture teaches us, that to throw our ſelves into Dangers, out of which we fore-ſee it will be impoſſible to eſcape, is to tempt God, who abandons thoſe that run headlong into it; that Chriſtian Prudence, the Charity they owed to their Wives and Children, and love of their own Perſons, did oblige them to follow the Example of the other Inhabitants of the Valleys; that their Prince looking on them as Criminals, would confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Goods, and would make them undergo the moſt ignominious puniſhments, if they perſiſted in their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. That ſince Divine Providence had bleſs'd with ſucceſs the Cares of thoſe that interceeded for them, it was viſible that ſhe was willing to diſingage them from this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98823:30"/> difficult paſſage; that having obtained ſome mitigation in the execution of the Edict, they ought to take hold of it; that it was not the fault of thoſe that employed themſelves for them, that their condition was not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that they ſhould aſſure themſelves, that there would be ſaved no labour to procure them ſome more advantages; but in caſe this ſhould be impoſſible, they ought to accept what was offered them, becauſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering their condition, they could not offer to capitulate with their Prince who had great Forces to oblige them to obedience; that in caſe they refuſed to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his will, their obſtinacy would cauſe themſelves not only the loſs of their bodies, but their very ſouls; and that they had reaſon to fear that thoſe who ſhould eſcape the ſword of their Perſecutors, would at laſt be overcome by the rigour of the hardſhips which they would be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to undergo, to make them change their Religion; that they had no reaſon to fear that leave to retreat whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they pleaſed, was granted them as a ſnare to intrap them, becauſe the Court had given them ſuch Securities that ought to ſet their minds at reſt concerning that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and perſwade them of the ſincerity of his Royal Highneſs's intention, who would not give leave that any thing ſhould be undertaken contrary to his promiſe, nor to blaſt a publick perfidiouſneſs on his glory and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor fall ſhort in his regards which he has had till now for the Evangelical Cantons; that in caſe they had been willing to ſurprize them, it might eaſily have been done at the firſt, but that the Prince would not ſuffer it, and that he would not ſuffer it for the future; that in fine, the Troops of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were ready to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack them from every ſide; and that they ought to be ſure that no harm would be done them, in caſe they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves to his Royal Highneſs's order.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Ambaſſadors having conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at leaſure the laſt Edict of his Royal Highneſs, found that the Inhabitants of the Valleys could not ſubmit to it without expoſing themſelves to very great inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, and reſolved to endeavour a new to get them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98823:31"/> ſome more advantageous conditions; and to this effect they deſired the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> to procure them an Audience of his Royal Highneſs, and having obtain'd it, they did repreſent to him, That having made ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon his Royal Highneſs's laſt Edict, they had taken the liberty to make ſome Obſervations upon three principal Points contained therein, to wit, 1. Upon that which allows the Inhabitants of the Valleys but ten days to retreat out of his Territories. 2. Upon that which preſcribes them the number of ſix Truſtees for the ſale of their Goods. 3. Upon that which gives them only leave to ſell their Goods within three months; and that they deſire his Royal Highneſs to look upon the Remarks they had ſet down in the Memorial, which they did preſent him, and to conſider that a mitigation of his Edict, they ſo much wiſht for, would be of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to him, but that it was of great importance to his miſerable Subjects, who had ſo profound a reſpect, and ſo fervent a love for their Soveraign, that they could not prevaile with themſelves to retreat out of his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and that conſidered with the greateſt trouble in the World, that abandoning their native Country they ſhould be deprived of the pleaſure which they had to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalize from time to time their Loyalty, taking hold on all occaſions to expoſe their lives in his ſervice: That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they hoped that his Royal Highneſs would make uſe of his clemency on their behalf, and to give neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary orders to put them in a condition to retreat conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently out of his Territories, and to carry along with them what they ſhould be able to get together out of their ſhip-wrack'd Fortunes; and that by theſe means he would give to their Excellencies the Proteſtant Cantons, a freſh reaſon to continue in that affection and reſpect they have always had for the Royal Houſe of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and in their Particular they would let them know that their good offices had not been unprofitable to thoſe Wretches they did interceed for.</p>
            <p>The Duke anſwered the Ambaſſadors, That in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Proteſtant Cantons, he had given his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98823:31"/> People great marks of an extraordinary clemency; that he had not chaſtiſed them according to their deſerts, but that he had expected with patience that his people ſhould come to themſelves, and conſider their duty; and that having puſhed their Rebellion to an extremity, and given him new reaſons of complaint, by thoſe Inſolencies they had lately committed, they had bound up his hands, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he could not grant them their requeſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wounding his reputation and authority; that the condeſcention he has had for them, had drawn upon him the reproaches of <hi>France,</hi> that nevertheleſs he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling they ſhould enjoy the benefit of his Edict; and that in caſe they would obtain ſome mitigation of the orders therein contained, they ought to render themſelves wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it in laying down their Arms, and ſubmitting themſelves to his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the Ambaſſadors preſented his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs their Memorial, with the following Contents:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>YOur Royal Highneſs is humbly petitioned to conſider, that he that will or ſhall retreat out of the Valleys by vertue of your publiſhed Order, is obliged to prepare himſelf for his departure, for the tranſport of his Wife, his Children, and his Goods, that will be neceſſary to him; that he will be obliged to diſpoſe in ſeveral places what he cannot carry along with him; that he must provide for the ſale of his Corn, of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, of his Wine, of his Cattle, which he would not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to leave at random; and that he cannot trust with his Procurator at <hi>Lucerne,</hi> and that conſequently by reaſon of the diſtance of the place, will be incapable to take care of it; that within the term of eight days he will not be able to come to an account either with his Creditors or his Debtors, becauſe thoſe he has to do with do not live in the Valleys, or becauſe there may be ſome accounts that cannot be regulated but by arbitrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that in conſideration of Goods immovable, there is to be made an exact deſcription of the Vine-yards, Meadows, Fields, and Woods, whoſe boundaries and limits are to be marked out and diſcribed, as alſo of the rights thereunto belonging, and the ſums for which they are mortgaged, and that there ought
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98823:32"/> to be granted ſome particular Procurations to that purpoſe; Therefore your Royal Highneſs having been pleaſed by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of your juſtice and clemency, to grant to your Subjects of the Valleys leave to retreat where ever they pleaſe, and to ſell their Goods which they ſhall leave behind them, you would not be willing that this favour ſhould be unprofitable to them, by obſtructing the favour of this conceſſion by the ſhortneſs of time, to take away from them, with one hand what you had given them with the other. Your Royal Highneſs is alſo requeſted to conſider that ſix Truſtees are not enough for the ſale of Goods belonging to ſeveral hundreds of Families that ſhall be willing to retreat; that this Commiſſion cannot be given but to People of the Country, and conſequently to perſons without learning and without capacity, and taken up with their own affairs; that beſides, theſe Truſtees will be obliged to run to ſeveral places to find out Buyers, to let them have a view of the funds which they are to buy, that ſettlements must be made in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places before ſeveral Notaries, that they are to watch at the ſelling of a great number of movables that are diſperſed in ſeveral Houſes, to tell money, to change it, and to ſend it to them into foreign Countries, to find out ſome conveniencies for that purpoſe, to write to their Correſpondents for the clearing of ſeveral doubts that may be raiſed, to remove the obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they ſhall meet with, to defend themſelves against ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt demands, to receive Letters from thoſe they ſhall write to from the places of their retreate, to acquaint them with the ſtate of their affairs, and in a word, to be charged with a thouſand other occupations that we cannot now foreſee: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe your Royal Highneſs does not intend to enrich your ſelf with the Goods of your poor Subjects, nor to augment your revenues by their loſſes, you will be pleaſed to grant them leave to nominate twelve Perſons that within the time preſcribed by your Royal Highneſs, ſhall proceed to the ſale of the Goods of thoſe that ſhall be retreated: But becauſe it will undoubtedly happen, that within the term of three months, with what dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ſoever the Truſtees may proceede to the ſale of the Goods of the poor Refugees; there will be found few Chapmen, and that every body will expect the end of the term to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the neceſſity which the Truſtees will be driven to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98823:32"/> to diſpoſe of their Goods, and to have them from thoſe Wretches at an under price, by reaſon of their fear to loſe all, we are in hopes your Royal Highneſs will have the goodneſs to prevent this inconveniency, and according to the Agreements made in the year <hi>1663,</hi> with his late Royal Highneſs of glorious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, you will buy at a reaſonable price the movable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable Goods, that within the ſpace of three months ſhall not be ſold.</p>
                     <p>And becauſe your Royal Highneſs does diſtinguiſh yourſelf by your goodneſs and clemency, you are not willing without doubt to oblige any body to impoſſibilities, and therefore concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved newly brought to bed, or that are in the laſt month of their time, old and ſick Men, you will make no difficulty to diſpence in their favour with the Law you have preſcribed to others about their retreate, and exempt them from quartering Souldiers, who how well ſoever diſſiplined, cauſe always ſome diſorder, and carry into all places where they enter, as alſo to grant them leave to live and die in their Houſes without fear of being ill uſed, and of being ſpoiled of their Goods and Proviſions.</p>
                     <p>In fine, we inſtantly deſire your Royal Highneſs that you would be pleaſed to uſe your clemency towards thoſe of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, that are detained in your Priſons, and towards thoſe that have been taken up on that account, and that you will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mercifully to ſet them at liberty.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> receiving the Memorial of the Ambaſſadors, did promiſe to take it into his conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and told them that he would acquaint them with his will about it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time that the Ambaſſadors were buſie at <hi>Turine,</hi> to render the condition of the Inhabitants of the Valleys more advantageous, they took a reſolution that cauſed their total ruine; for inſtead that before the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the laſt Edict, the moſt part amongſt them were reſolved to look for a retreate ſome-where elſe, they did joyn all together by a common conſent, and formed a deſign to defend themſelves againſt thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that were in a readineſs to attack them.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98823:33"/>
            <p>The reaſons which they alledged in their Councel were, That his Royal Highneſs's Edict, to which they were commanded to ſubmit themſelves, did contain ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things which they could not allow, and others which they could in no manner execute: And <hi>firſt,</hi> they ſaid it was not reaſonable they ſhould declare themſelves guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Rebellion they were taxed with, becauſe they had done nothing againſt his Royal Highneſs's ſervice, but only that which they had been obliged to, to maintain the exerciſe of their Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, That they ought not to approve of the laſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, becauſe it confirm'd that of the 31ſt of <hi>January,</hi> by which they were deprived of the liberty to ſerve God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their faith.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, That they could not prevail with themſelves to obey that clauſe by which they were commanded to lay down their Arms, and that in caſe they ſhould ſubmit themſelves to it, they would expoſe themſelves to the loſs of their temporal and ſpiritual Happineſs, and would be forced to undergo the ſame misfortune which did hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to them in the former Perſecutions, and principally in that of the year 1655, which taught them, by a fatal experience, that they made no bones to break their word with them; and what confirmed them in their opinion was the approach of the Troops that advanced towards their Country, notwithſtanding the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> his promiſe, who did aſſure them, that they were not to enter into their Country, till after the term pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Edict.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, That the time which was given them for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of their departure being extreamly ſhort, they could not execute the Edict, conſidering the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Inhabitants of the Valleys, the great age of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons, and the ſickneſs of ſeveral others.</p>
            <p n="5">5thly, That it was impoſſible that the ſale of their Goods ſhould be made by Truſtees; that ſuppoſe they ſhould be reſolved to ſell them, it ſhould be upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to receive the price of it before their departure, or that it ſhould be put into the hands of the Ambaſſadors;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98823:33"/> and that there ſhould be procured the ſale of the Goods of thoſe ſcituate upon the Mountains, as well as of thoſe that were in the Plains, and of thoſe that were in the <hi>French</hi> K.'s Territories: And in fine, whereas this ſale ought to be made to <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, that they had reaſon to fear the Prieſts would hinder them to buy, being aſſured that they would not fail to be Maſters of all, after that all the Inhabitants of the Valleys ſhould be out of the Country.</p>
            <p n="6">6thly, That they had reaſon to fear all from thoſe that hold for a Maxim, <hi>That no faith ought to be kept with Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſters and moſt reaſonable Perſons of the Valleys did all they could to hinder this People from coming to this extremity; but all their reaſons they did employ to prevent this reſolution, were not capable to hinder them from being hurried away by the conduct of thoſe that flatter'd them with imaginary hopes; and theſe are the very Perſons that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering them to accept of the favour that was offer'd them, were the cauſe of their ruine. The reaſon may be ſeen in this following Letter, that was made uſe of to make them change their reſolution, and to precipitate them to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>Rocheplatte,
<date>April the 14th, 1686.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious and moſt Mighty LORDS,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Can find no means to contain the People of our Vallies in their Duty, and principally ſince a certain Miniſter (whoſe name you ſhall be informed of) is arrived here, who has at ſuch a rate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed our People with pretended Succours of all things, that there is no Miniſter in ſafety in his Church. Saving three Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Boby, Angrogne,</hi> and <hi>St. John,</hi> all was at quiet, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved intirely to ſubmit themſelves to your charity and conduct; and ſtill the moſt reaſonable might perhaps at laſt have prevailed with thoſe who err, as well out of ignorance, as for want of being well acquainted with your Excellencies; but amongſt all, my Church at <hi>Tour</hi> was intirely ſubmiſſive till his arrival, who has put us all in confuſion, ſave the moſt reaſonable, who deſire from you a Particuler to take them under your protection, in order to get them a free retreat to ſuch a place where they may ſerve God according to his Commandments. I conſecrate myſelf with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98823:34"/> found humility to render you my moſt humble reſpects, being with a profound ſubmiſſion</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your moſt Illuſtrious Excellencies moſt humble and obedient Servant,</hi> Girand, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Tour.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>In another Letter written by the Miniſter of the Churches of the Valleys, there is to be found a blanck for names, in the following words:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>MR. — Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Pinache,</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Pezonſe,</hi> is come from — where we are firmly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded he has received order to animate, as he does, all the World rather to die than to accept of the conditions of a Retreat, under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral promiſes.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors being acquainted with this reſolution of theirs, ſaw very well that conſidering the diſpoſition of this People, there was no appearance to make them change in their opinion, and to infuſe into them more reaſonable thoughts.</p>
            <p>Yet nevertheleſs they thought that they ought to make their laſt endeavours to oblige them to accept of the favour which their Prince did offer them, though it was not ſo large and advantagious as they might have wiſhed for: And whereas they conſidered that the only means to work in ſome meaſure upon their minds, was to render their retreat leſs inconvenient and leſs troubleſome than it was, according to the terms of the Edict, they applied themſelves to ſollicit for an Anſwer to the Memorial which they had preſented to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> that in caſe it was favourable they could make it known to thoſe of the Valleys, and to make uſe of as the ſtrongeſt reaſon for their perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>But his Anſwer was not ſuch as they expected, for the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> acquainted the Ambaſſador, that his Royal Highneſs would not make any larger Declaration con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the things contained in his laſt Edict, becauſe his Subjects were obſtinate in their Rebellion, and becauſe they refuſed to lay down their Arms, boaſting, that they were in a condition to reſiſt their Prince; that therefore his Royal Highneſs was reſolved to depart to morrow, and to go in perſon to make theſe Rebels conform to their duty. That concerning thoſe that would retreat ſome-where elſe, they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98823:34"/> ſhould faithfully enjoy the benefit of the Edict; and that thoſe that would not ſubmit to it, ſhould receive their ſo-much-deſerved puniſhment.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as they had left the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas,</hi> they diſpatched an Expreſs to thoſe in the Valleys, and gave them advice of the ill ſucceſs of their Negotiation, by the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letter:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>AT the ſecret Audience which we had of his Royal Highneſs, your Prince, we have inſtantly deſired him, that he would he pleaſed to grant you a retreat out of his Territories upon more gracious conditions then thoſe that are expreſſed by the laſt Edict; and we have repreſented to him as well by word of mouth, as by our Memorial, all the reaſons that might be capable to move and to prevail with him to mitigate the Orders he has already publiſhed againſt you: We did ſolicit him to grant you a longer term to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe yourſelves to ſo troubleſome a retreat, and to ſell your Goods, and that he would be pleaſed to augment the number of the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees charged to ſell them; to give leave that the aged, ſick, and infirm perſons, and Women newly brought to bed, or that were big with child might ſtay behind in the Country without being expoſed to any ill uſage, and without being obliged to quarter Souldiers; and in fine, to give order that his Procurators might ſell the Goods that ſhould not be vended within the time preſcribed by his Edict: But we have not been able to obtain the leaſt thing from his Royal Highneſs, becauſe he has been informed that you are up in Arms to obſtruct the execution of his orders. We have alſo endeavoured to perſwade the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> that he would be pleaſed to imploy his credit with his Royal Highneſs, to diſpoſe him to grant us what we deſired in your favour; but he has given us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that as long as you ſhall keep in Arms, there are no hopes for you. His Royal Highneſs departs this day for <hi>Precairas,</hi> and we have had our Audience of Conge, with a deſign to return immediately into our Country, except God's providence give us ſome more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable occaſion to ſerve you; and ſince without taking notice of ſome wiſe Mens counſels, you reſign the event of your Affairs to God's providence, we beſeech him that he would be pleaſed to aſſiſt you in your calamity, and direct all to his glory, and your temporal and ſpiritual welfare; Reſting, after we have recommended you to God Almighty's favour, <hi>&amp;c. </hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Turine,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98823:35"/>
            <p>Altho' the Ambaſſadors found the Affairs of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Valleys to be in a deſperate condition, and that it was impoſſible for them to prevent their misfortune, yet they would not abandon them, and they thought it would be of ſome profit to them, if they followed his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the Camp, therefore they deſired the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas</hi> to ask his Royal Highneſs's leave for it: But the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs told them, that their preſence might give ſome jealouſie to the Ambaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> and the Pope, and that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as his Royal Highneſs had ſeveral great reaſons not to diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige the Moſt Chriſtian King, the Ambaſſadors would oblige him not to inſiſt upon this demand, Affairs being in ſuch a condition, that how diſpoſed ſoever his Royal Highneſs were to give them ſome marks of his conſiderations for them, he was in no capacity to let them ſee how much reflection he made upon their Interceſſion.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Ambaſſadors that had had their Audience of Conge, upon condition nevertheleſs, that in caſe there ſhould happen an accident that might oblige them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to appear at Court, there ſhould be had all deference for them, that was due to their Character, reſolved to return to their own Country, according to the order which they had received ſome few days before from their Soveraigns, in a Letter written to them from <hi>Zuric,</hi> in which the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Cantons commanded them to abandon their Negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in caſe they did judge it would be fruitleſs.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, whereas they thought that the Marqueſs of <hi>St. Thomas,</hi> or the other Miniſters might be able to find ſome favourable moment to prevail with his Royal Highneſs to make uſe of his clemency towards his poor Subjects of the Valleys, they reſolved to pay them a viſit, to deſire them to have compaſſion upon thoſe Wretches, and to render them on this occaſion all the good offices they might be capable of; but becauſe the Court was obliged to depart in a hurry, it was impoſſible for them to execute their deſign, and they were obliged to make thoſe inſtances to them by writing, which they could not do by word of mouth: and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived preſently after the Marqueſs's anſwer, who did aſſure them, that he would take hold of all overtures which thoſe of the Valleys could furniſh him with to employ himſelf for them.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98823:35"/>
            <p>A few days before their departure, they received two Letters out of the Valleys, one writ by all the Commonalties to the Evangelical Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, in the following manner:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Moſt High, Mighty, and Soveraign Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r Churches have for a long time experimented, and principally in theſe unhappy Troubles that have happened to them, the incomparable chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and fatherly affection of your Excellencies towards them, and ſtill very lately, by ſending our Lords the Ambaſſadors to his Royal Highneſs, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the Order of the 31st of <hi>January</hi> last, publiſhed against us, as we have been informed of, by the Letter which you have been pleaſed to direct to us; We are not able enough to acknowledge the cares, troubles, and pains which our Lords the Ambaſſadors have taken in our favour and preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, towards our Soveraign, and had they met with hearts diſpoſed to our welfare and quietneſs, their Interceſſions would not have failed of being ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful; but it ought to be confeſſed, that our condition is very bad from that ſide, conſidering the World; we render nevertheleſs to your Excellencies, with all the ſentiments of acknowledgments we are capable of, our most humble and hearty thanks for ſo many favours we have received from their ſo Holy and Chriſtian Charity: We are very ſenſible, and confeſs it, tho' with a great confuſion, that our Lords the Ambaſſadors have not had from our People all that ſatisfaction that might have been wiſht for, concerning their reſignation into your hands: but we most humbly beſeech you to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their charity and ſupport towards a People that make to themſelves a point of Conſcience and Honour to preſerve their Religion in their native Country, where it has been a long time miraculouſly preſerved: We are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible that as to the World, our ruine is unavoidable, but we are in hopes that God will revenge his quarrel, and that good and charitable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will not abandon us, and principally we put our trust under God, unto your Excellencies, and throw ourſelves into their fatherly arms, beſeeching you for the compaſſion of God, and in the name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, our common Father and Saviour, not to deprive us of your charity and affection, and to throw the eyes of your clemency and tenderneſs upon ſo many poor Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, little Children, and other weak miſerable Perſons, as to the World, to let them feel the favourable effects of your Chriſtian Goodneſs: We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Lord that he would be pleaſed to be the perpetual Preſerver of your Excellencies, and the abundant Rewarder of all your Holy and Chriſtian Charities; and are with all the veneration imaginable,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Moſt High, Mighty, and Soveraign Lords, your Excellencies Moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt obliged Servants,</hi> The Miniſters, Ancients, and other Directors of the Churches of the Valleys in <hi>Plemont,</hi> and for All, <hi>S. Baſtie,</hi> Moderator; <hi>Gr. Matant,</hi> Miniſter.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The Letter which the Miniſters writ to the Ambaſſadors, was to this purpoſe:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:98823:36"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lords,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>WE do intend to communicate immediately to our Commonalti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Excellencies Letters: We might have wiſht that they had be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> mindful of thoſe wiſe Counſels your Excellencies have given them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vent ſuch a danger and deſolation that in all humane probability is un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able: We pray to God that he would be pleaſed to crown their reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tho' against all appearance, with ſucceſs, and to ſtrengthen their in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and feebleneſs. I do believe that all the Miniſters do deſign to live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> die amongst them, becauſe your Excellencies do not diſapprove it: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed it would neither be honest nor excuſable to abandon them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> juncture of time; and we would certainly have reaſon to think o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> guilty in part of their loſs, becauſe a good Shepheard is bound to la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> his life for his Flock. We continue to give your Excellencies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> humble thanks for thoſe Troubles and infatigable Cares you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> our welfare and ſubſiſtance; and we conjure you by the compaſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and by the charity of Jeſus Christ, not to forget us, but whether it be your ſtay at <hi>Turin,</hi> or after your return to the most High and Migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtant Cantons, to favour us with your Affection and Chriſtian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> on all occaſions. We pray our Great God and Saviour, that he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> pleaſed to reward the Pains and Charities of your Excellencies towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Churches, with his most precious bleſſings in Heaven and Earth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver your ſacred perſons with his inviolable protection: Theſe are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and fervent Wiſhes of thoſe that are with a profound reſpect,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>My Lords,</salute> 
                        <signed>
                           <hi> your Excellencies moſt humble and obedient Servant</hi> The Miniſters of the Evangelical Churches of the Valleys of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Angrogne, Rerouſe, St. Martin,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Piemont,</hi> and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of All, <hi>S. Baſtie,</hi> Miniſter.</signed>
                        <dateline>Ang.
<date>April <hi>17, 1686.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The Inhabitants of the Valleys being diſpoſed in this manner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> juſt now repreſented, and the D. of <hi>Savoy</hi> being departed for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeemed the Ambaſſadors had no more buſineſs at Court, and that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> go on their journey: but becauſe it might happen that this People, the danger near, and the Troops in a condition to attack them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> willing to make uſe of the Prince's clemency, by the interceſſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſſadors; they thought that they ought not to leave them, till they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that the Armies, was entred into their Country, and that they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> formed of the ſucceſs of this Expedition: But having heard that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had no ſooner appeared in the Valleys, but that thoſe of <hi>St. Martin</hi> taken themſelves to their heels, and that the Prince's Troops having the Paſſages about <hi>Angrogne,</hi> ſound no where the leaſt reſiſtance. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were ſenſible that they had no more buſineſs in <hi>Piemont,</hi> and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> extreamly troubled that they had not been able to prevent the Deſola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> theſe precious Remains of the <hi>Vaudois</hi> Churches. And being arrived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Country, they gave an account of their Embaſſy to their Soveraign judging of their Negotiation not by its ſucceſs, but by their conduct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> having aſſured them that they were well ſatisfied with the zeal and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they had ſhewed during the whole courſe of this difficult Affair, gav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Thanks for the Cares they had taken to fill up worthily the Employ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they had been honoured with.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
